<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-03T18:43:58+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Fedbot</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><entry><title type="html">Goolsbee Sees Solid Job Market, But Bumpy Inflation Path Clouds Rate Cut Timing</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/05/03/goolsbee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goolsbee Sees Solid Job Market, But Bumpy Inflation Path Clouds Rate Cut Timing" /><published>2024-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/05/03/goolsbee</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/05/03/goolsbee.html"><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.</p>

<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<div id="youtube-player-container"></div>

<!-- Load the IFrame Player API code asynchronously -->
<script src="https://www.youtube.com/iframe_api"></script>

<script>
  var player;
  function onYouTubeIframeAPIReady() {
    player = new YT.Player('youtube-player-container', {
      height: '315',
      width: '560',
      videoId: 'w98BZoWvQ2U'
    });
  };

function seekToTime(timestamp) {
  var timeArr = timestamp.split(":");
  var hours = 0;
  var minutes = 0;
  var seconds = 0;

  // Check if the timestamp includes hours
  if (timeArr.length === 3) {
    hours = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[2], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 2) {
    // If the timestamp is only minutes and seconds
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 1) {
    // If the timestamp is only seconds
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
  }

  // Calculate total seconds
  var totalSeconds = hours * 3600 + minutes * 60 + seconds;

  // Seek to the specified time if possible
  if (player && player.seekTo) {
    player.seekTo(totalSeconds, true);
  }
}


// Attach click event listeners to each sentence
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function() {
  document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(span) {
    span.addEventListener("click", function() {
      // Remove highlighting/underscore from all spans
      document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(otherSpan) {
        otherSpan.classList.remove("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      });
      
      // Add highlighting/underscore to the clicked span
      this.classList.add("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      
      // Seek the video to the timestamp
      var timestamp = this.getAttribute("data-timestamp");
      seekToTime(timestamp);
    });
  });
});

</script>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-1" data-timestamp="00:00" class="neutral">Welcome to the campus of Stanford University, the Hoover Institution's Monetary Policy Conference.</span> <span id="sentence-2" data-timestamp="00:07" class="neutral">And we're very excited this morning to have with us Austan Goolsbee, who is the president of the Chicago Federal Reserve Bank.</span> <span id="sentence-3" data-timestamp="00:15" class="neutral">Thank you for making time for us this morning when all of a sudden the disappointment that the markets had on Wednesday went away.</span> <span id="sentence-4" data-timestamp="00:23" class="neutral bold">Everybody's happy this morning because jobs came in lower than expected, 175,000.</span> <span id="sentence-5" data-timestamp="00:28" class="neutral bold">What was your reaction?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-6" data-timestamp="00:30" class="neutral bold">Well, I mean, 175,000 is a very solid report.</span> <span id="sentence-7" data-timestamp="00:35" class="neutral">The sum of the root of our frictions here might be there's a kind of a day traders timetable and there's an economic timetable for setting monetary policy.</span> <span id="sentence-8" data-timestamp="00:44" class="neutral">Of course, you got to take a longer arc view on inflation, on employment.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-9" data-timestamp="00:49" class="dovish">And we're just trying to figure out after the excellent dual mandate performance of 2023, let's call it where inflation fell almost as much as it has fallen on record, and it did so without a recession.</span> <span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="01:04" class="dovish">How much can we continue that into 2024?</span> <span id="sentence-11" data-timestamp="01:07" class="hawkish bold">We hit a bump for sure at the start of the year on the inflation front.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-12" data-timestamp="01:17" class="neutral">And now everybody's just got to take a step back and try to figure out, is that a sign that the economy's overheating or is that a sign of some other thing?</span> <span id="sentence-13" data-timestamp="01:26" class="dovish bold">The more jobs reports you get like this where they're solid, but it's clearly moving back into something that looks like pre-COVID and conventional times, the more confident we can be that the economy's not overheating.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-14" data-timestamp="01:43" class="neutral">But we just got to we got to just got to watch this.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-15" data-timestamp="01:46" class="neutral">You are one of the I don't want to use the word dovish, but more optimistic people about the possibility that rates could be cut this year.</span> <span id="sentence-16" data-timestamp="01:54" class="neutral">How do you feel now?</span> <span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="01:56" class="neutral">We do see this slowdown.</span> <span id="sentence-18" data-timestamp="01:59" class="neutral">The ISM numbers show slowdowns.</span> <span id="sentence-19" data-timestamp="02:01" class="neutral">Spending numbers were lower than anticipated and lower than in the last quarter.</span> <span id="sentence-20" data-timestamp="02:06" class="neutral">Are we setting up to go back to the idea that rate cuts are going to happen this year?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="02:11" class="neutral bold">I don't like committing to in our hands of even for the next meeting, much less when it comes to the fall and going into next year.</span> <span id="sentence-22" data-timestamp="02:20" class="dovish">I will say the I was optimistic in 2023 that we could hit what I was calling the Golden Path, that there were reasons why in an unprecedented way we potentially could get inflation down significantly without having a big recession, which previous 2023 </span> <span id="sentence-23" data-timestamp="02:39" class="dovish">that really doesn't happen.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="02:44" class="dovish">We did that in 23 as we're looking in 24.</span> <span id="sentence-25" data-timestamp="02:49" class="hawkish bold">Like I said, we clearly hit a bump at the start of this year and we've just got to get comfort that it's not a sign of of a re-acceleration of the economy.</span> <span id="sentence-26" data-timestamp="03:00" class="neutral">And we got some cross-currents going.</span> <span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="03:03" class="neutral">There's no question about that.</span> <span id="sentence-28" data-timestamp="03:05" class="neutral bold">I think what's happened so far in the job market this year is a little colored by...</span><span id="sentence-29" data-timestamp="03:17" class="neutral">You got to take into account that we actually had significantly more immigration than we anticipated or then we thought at the time.</span> <span id="sentence-30" data-timestamp="03:28" class="neutral">So everything's got to kind of be normed to a per capita basis, and that makes aggregate numbers like aggregate GDP growth or aggregate consumption or aggregate payroll growth.</span> <span id="sentence-31" data-timestamp="03:39" class="neutral">You got to scale it down a bit. And we're still trying to wrap our head around how much.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-32" data-timestamp="03:43" class="neutral">What about the idea of the need to raise rates?</span> <span id="sentence-33" data-timestamp="03:49" class="neutral">The chairman was asked about it a number of times on Wednesday, said it didn't seem like something that was going to happen.</span> <span id="sentence-34" data-timestamp="03:55" class="neutral bold">Is it at all on the table for you?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-35" data-timestamp="03:57" class="neutral bold">Look, like I say, I don't like speculating when we're going to get a lot of information before the next meeting and before all the meetings for the rest of the year.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-36" data-timestamp="04:15" class="dovish">In an unclear way, I say don't think that nothing is never not on the table.</span> <span id="sentence-37" data-timestamp="04:19" class="neutral">You know, the job of a central banker is to be paranoid about everything at all times and to have thought through plans and how could we react to different circumstances.</span> <span id="sentence-38" data-timestamp="04:30" class="neutral">So it's not productive to say something's not on the table ever.</span> <span id="sentence-39" data-timestamp="04:35" class="neutral">Something is on the table.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-40" data-timestamp="04:37" class="neutral">I just think it's we're going to we're going to find out this data, these data and the key element on the economic timetable, not the market trading timetable is are we continuing the progress slow and steady that we saw last year, or is some other thing happening that we're accelerating? The more job's numbers like the ones we saw today,</span> <span id="sentence-41" data-timestamp="05:00" class="neutral">the more you see easing of inflation, the more comfort we would have, </span><span id="sentence-42" data-timestamp="05:08" class="neutral">I would have on the committee, I don't speak for anybody else and if it goes the other way, we'll react to that.</span> <span id="sentence-43" data-timestamp="05:15" class="neutral">You know, that's the Midwestern way is there is no bad weather.</span> <span id="sentence-44" data-timestamp="05:19" class="neutral">There's only bad clothing.</span> <span id="sentence-45" data-timestamp="05:21" class="neutral">You know, we will deal with it.</span> <span id="sentence-46" data-timestamp="05:23" class="neutral">I mean, we're we're out here at Stanford.</span> <span id="sentence-47" data-timestamp="05:25" class="neutral">There's definitely no bad weather.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-48" data-timestamp="05:27" class="neutral">But back in Chicago, you know, it's different.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-49" data-timestamp="05:31" class="neutral">Well, to drill down on that a little bit.</span> <span id="sentence-50" data-timestamp="05:34" class="neutral bold">The question then becomes, do you think monetary policy is tight enough?</span> <span id="sentence-51" data-timestamp="05:38" class="neutral bold">And if so, how do you square that with the idea that inflation has started going up again?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-52" data-timestamp="05:44" class="hawkish bold">There's two separate parts to that.</span> <span id="sentence-53" data-timestamp="05:46" class="hawkish bold">The first is how restrictive is monetary policy?</span> <span id="sentence-54" data-timestamp="05:49" class="hawkish bold">I think it's restrictive.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-55" data-timestamp="05:51" class="hawkish bold">I think if you look at the real federal funds rate, it's high.</span> <span id="sentence-56" data-timestamp="05:55" class="hawkish bold">It's as high as it's been in some decades.</span> <span id="sentence-57" data-timestamp="05:58" class="hawkish bold">And I think that lately, if you look at the interests, interest rate, sensitive parts of the economy, you see that restrictiveness.</span> <span id="sentence-58" data-timestamp="06:08" class="neutral bold">The second part of the question is, well, then what happened with inflation?</span> <span id="sentence-59" data-timestamp="06:13" class="neutral bold">And I think the answer but that's partly what we're trying to find out is there's a whole lot of other things besides monetary policy and besides the aggregate stated demand that drive inflation rates.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-60" data-timestamp="06:25" class="neutral">And you've definitely seen things happening on the supply side of the economy with shipping and bridges and canals, shutdowns and things like that.</span> <span id="sentence-61" data-timestamp="06:35" class="neutral">Commodity prices, you've seen movement, energy prices, you've seen movement.</span> <span id="sentence-62" data-timestamp="06:40" class="neutral">And so we've just got to get a better, more comfort, I think, on this question of are we on the long arc that we saw all of last year and especially the second half of last year, where inflation's steadily coming down or are we in some different environment?</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-63" data-timestamp="07:00" class="neutral">If you're in some different environment, is it things that monetary policy can affect?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-64" data-timestamp="07:07" class="neutral">It might be, you know, if it's all supply shock.</span> <span id="sentence-65" data-timestamp="07:10" class="neutral">Probably not.</span> <span id="sentence-66" data-timestamp="07:11" class="neutral">I mean, we kind of saw that dynamic play out at the beginning of the pandemic when the supply chains shut down.</span> <span id="sentence-67" data-timestamp="07:18" class="neutral">So that's another important aspect that's in this effort.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-68" data-timestamp="07:29" class="neutral">You know, as I kind of say, that everyone thinks it's a battle between dovishness and hawkishness, but it's really it's not about the birds, it's the data dogs.</span> <span id="sentence-69" data-timestamp="07:39" class="neutral">And the first rule of the data dogs is know when to walk and know when to sniff.</span> <span id="sentence-70" data-timestamp="07:45" class="neutral">And, you know, the time to sniff is when we're trying to figure these out.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b> <span id="sentence-71" data-timestamp="07:50" class="neutral">Well, when you look at the overall economy, we mentioned earlier that we're seeing some slowdown.</span> <span id="sentence-72" data-timestamp="07:56" class="neutral">Fed officials have said we can wait because the economy is in good shape.</span> <span id="sentence-73" data-timestamp="08:01" class="neutral bold">But how much do you worry that you're going to slow the economy too much?</span> <span id="sentence-74" data-timestamp="08:05" class="neutral">And because things like unemployment are a lagging indicator that you'll find yourself with really slow growth or recession before you can react?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-75" data-timestamp="08:15" class="neutral bold">Look, that's the balance that you have to strike, that delicate balance.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-76" data-timestamp="08:20" class="neutral">That's the that's the dual mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-77" data-timestamp="08:23" class="hawkish">And there was a time when the job market was explosively hot and inflation was well off the chart in worse than we wanted.</span> <span id="sentence-78" data-timestamp="08:34" class="hawkish">And there's no balance in an environment like that.</span> <span id="sentence-79" data-timestamp="08:38" class="hawkish">You're just trying to get the inflation rate down.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-80" data-timestamp="08:47" class="dovish bold">If we remain as restrictive as this for too long, we're in my view, definitely going to have to be thinking about the employment side of the mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-81" data-timestamp="08:56" class="neutral">So far, we've got some cross-currents going.</span> <span id="sentence-82" data-timestamp="08:59" class="neutral bold">As I say, the job numbers today are solid.</span> <span id="sentence-83" data-timestamp="09:03" class="dovish">There's not in a previous world, if you said you're getting jobs numbers in 175,000 - 200,000 range, people be quite happy with that.</span> <span id="sentence-84" data-timestamp="09:10" class="neutral">So we'll just have to see.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-85" data-timestamp="09:13" class="neutral">It is true that in normal times, when the business cycle turns the wrong way, it doesn't do so.</span> <span id="sentence-86" data-timestamp="09:21" class="neutral">It's not subtle, there's no subtlety about it.</span> <span id="sentence-87" data-timestamp="09:24" class="hawkish">The unemployment rate goes up quite significantly.</span> <span id="sentence-88" data-timestamp="09:27" class="hawkish">You see your credit delinquencies deteriorate a lot.</span> <span id="sentence-89" data-timestamp="09:31" class="hawkish">You see durable goods manufacturing, which are and other cyclically sensitive sectors deteriorate it in a noticeable way.</span> <span id="sentence-90" data-timestamp="09:40" class="dovish">And you haven't really seen that.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-91" data-timestamp="09:45" class="neutral">And that's part of where we're that's part of where we're monitoring.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b><span id="sentence-92" data-timestamp="09:49" class="neutral">You have a manufacturing intensive district, but also a lot of services.</span> <span id="sentence-93" data-timestamp="09:54" class="neutral">What are CEOs telling you about their vision for what's coming and they're planning in terms of employment and in terms of prices?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b><span id="sentence-96" data-timestamp="10:05" class="neutral">As you point out, the Chicago Fed's district is the most manufacturing intensity of all the Fed, and four of the five most manufacturing intensive states are in the are in the district.</span> <span id="sentence-97" data-timestamp="10:18" class="neutral">Our business contacts on the manufacturing side mostly they convey more of the same that that 2024 it's not accelerating.</span> <span id="sentence-98" data-timestamp="10:27" class="neutral">It's not decelerating.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-99" data-timestamp="10:33" class="neutral">They're just trudging along in a decent environment.</span> <span id="sentence-100" data-timestamp="10:37" class="neutral">I think we still are seeing play out We've we got past the supply chain bottlenecks.</span> <span id="sentence-101" data-timestamp="10:44" class="neutral">You don't hear a lot of input on that but we're still in the what you might call the consumer spending transformation that in Covid services went down, which normally doesn't happen in a recession because people couldn't go to the dentist and people couldn't go to the movies or see sports and they shifted to buying physical goods.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-102" data-timestamp="11:06" class="neutral">So the share of their budget that they spent on manufactured goods went way up and we're shifting back.</span> <span id="sentence-103" data-timestamp="11:13" class="neutral">You're seeing that shift back.</span> <span id="sentence-104" data-timestamp="11:15" class="neutral">So that's playing out in manufacturing, too.</span></p>

<p><b>Michael McKee:</b><span id="sentence-105" data-timestamp="11:19" class="neutral">Very quick last question or two questions you can answer yes or no.</span> <span id="sentence-106" data-timestamp="11:23" class="neutral">The things people wanted me to ask you, was there any talk at the meeting of raising rates or about raising rates?</span> <span id="sentence-107" data-timestamp="11:30" class="neutral">And did you have an advanced look at the job's numbers?</span> </p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b><span id="sentence-109" data-timestamp="11:35" class="neutral">Okay. You don't have an advance.</span> <span id="sentence-110" data-timestamp="11:36" class="neutral">Look at the jobs numbers.</span> <span id="sentence-111" data-timestamp="11:38" class="neutral">You're going to have to wait five years to get the transcript from the meetings.</span> <span id="sentence-112" data-timestamp="11:42" class="neutral">The minutes will come out in a few weeks.</span> <span id="sentence-113" data-timestamp="11:44" class="neutral">So I'm definitely not going to say what people talk about.</span> <span id="sentence-114" data-timestamp="11:49" class="neutral">I as you know, I never put anything on the table or off the table.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-115" data-timestamp="11:55" class="neutral">I try to be as paranoid as possible about all potentialities and what could happen.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Goolsbee" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fed Chair Sees Possible Rate Cut Paths, But Timing Hinges on Inflation Data</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/presser/2024/05/01/powell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fed Chair Sees Possible Rate Cut Paths, But Timing Hinges on Inflation Data" /><published>2024-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/presser/2024/05/01/powell</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/presser/2024/05/01/powell.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}
</style>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. Good afternoon.</span> <span class="neutral">My colleagues and I remain squarely focused on our dual mandate to promote maximum employment and stable prices for the American people.</span> <span class="neutral">The economy has made considerable progress toward our dual mandate objectives.</span> <span class="dovish bold">Inflation has eased substantially over the past year while the labor market has remained strong and that's very good news.</span> <span class="neutral bold">But inflation is still too high, further progress in bringing it down is not assured, and the path forward is uncertain.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">We are fully committed to returning inflation to our 2 percent goal.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Restoring price stability is essential to achieve a sustainably strong labor market that benefits all.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">Today, the FOMC decided to leave our policy interest rate unchanged and to continue to reduce our securities holdings, though at a slower pace.</span> <span class="dovish bold">Our restrictive stance of monetary policy has been putting downward pressure on economic activity and inflation, and the risks to achieving our employment and inflation goals have moved toward better balance over the past year.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">However, in recent months inflation has shown a lack of further progress toward our 2 percent objective, and we remain highly attentive to inflation risks.</span> <span class="neutral">I will have more to say about monetary policy after briefly reviewing economic developments.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral">Recent indicators suggest that economic activity has continued to expand at a solid pace.</span> <span class="neutral">Although GDP growth moderated from 3.4 percent in the fourth quarter of last year to 1.6 percent in the first quarter, Private Domestic Final Purchases, which excludes inventory investment, government spending and net exports, and usually sends a clearer signal on underlying demand, was 3.1 percent in the first quarter, as strong as the second half of 2023.</span> <span class="neutral">Consumer spending has been robust over the past several quarters, even as high interest rates have weighed on housing and equipment investment.</span> <span class="neutral">Improving supply conditions have supported resilient demand and the strong performance of the U.S. economy over the past year.</span></p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">The labor market remains relatively tight, but supply and demand conditions have come into better balance.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Payroll job gains averaged 276 thousand jobs per month in the first quarter, while the unemployment rate remains low at 3.8 percent.</span> <span class="dovish bold">Strong job creation over the past year has been accompanied by an increase in the supply of workers, reflecting increases in participation among individuals aged 25 to 54 years and a continued strong pace of immigration.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">Nominal wage growth has eased over the past year and the jobs-to-workers gap has narrowed, but labor demand still exceeds the supply of available workers.</span></p>
<p><span class="dovish bold">Inflation has eased notably over the past year but remains above our longer-run goal of 2 percent.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Total PCE prices rose 2.7 percent over the 12 months ending in March; excluding the volatile food and energy categories, core PCE prices rose 2.8 percent.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">The inflation data received so far this year have been higher than expected.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Although some measures of short-term inflation expectations have increased in recent months, longer-term inflation expectations appear to remain well anchored, as reflected in a broad range of surveys of households, businesses, and forecasters, as well as measures from financial markets.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral">The Fed's monetary policy actions are guided by our mandate to promote maximum employment and stable prices for the American people.</span> <span class="dovish">My colleagues and I are acutely aware that high inflation imposes significant hardship as it erodes purchasing power, especially for those least able to meet the higher costs of essentials like food, housing, and transportation.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">We are strongly committed to returning inflation to our 2 percent objective.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">The Committee decided at today's meeting to maintain the target range for the federal funds rate at 5-1/4 to 5-1/2 percent and to continue the process of significantly reducing our securities holdings, though at a slower pace.</span> <span class="dovish bold">Over the past year, as labor market tightness has eased and inflation has declined, the risks to achieving our employment and inflation goals have moved toward better balance.</span> <span class="hawkish">The economic outlook is uncertain, however, and we remain highly attentive to inflation risks.</span></p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">We have stated that we do not expect it will be appropriate to reduce the target range for the federal funds rate until we have gained greater confidence that inflation is moving sustainably toward 2 percent.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">So far this year, the data have not given us that greater confidence.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">In particular, and as I noted earlier, readings on inflation have come in above expectations.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">It is likely that gaining such greater confidence will take longer than previously expected.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">We are prepared to maintain the current target range for the federal funds rate for as long as appropriate.</span> <span class="dovish bold">We are also prepared to respond to an unexpected weakening in the labor market.</span></p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">We know that reducing policy restraint too soon or too much could result in a reversal of the progress we have seen on inflation.</span> <span class="dovish bold">At the same time, reducing policy restraint too late or too little could unduly weaken economic activity and employment.</span> <span class="neutral bold">In considering any adjustments to the target range for the federal funds rate, the Committee will carefully assess incoming data, the evolving outlook, and the balance of risks.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Policy is well positioned to deal with the risks and uncertainties that we face in pursuing both sides of our dual mandate.</span> <span class="neutral bold">We will continue to make decisions meeting by meeting.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">Turning to our balance sheet, the Committee decided at today's meeting to slow the pace of decline in our securities holdings, consistent with the plans we released previously.</span> <span class="neutral">Specifically, the cap on Treasury redemptions will be lowered from the current $60 billion per month to $25 billion per month as of June 1.</span> <span class="neutral">Consistent with the Committee's intention to hold primarily Treasury securities in the longer run, we are leaving the cap on agency securities unchanged per month and will reinvest any proceeds in excess of this cap in Treasury securities.</span> <span class="neutral">With principal payments on agency securities currently running at about $15 billion per month, total portfolio runoff will amount to roughly $40 billion per month.</span> <span class="neutral">The decision to slow the pace of runoff does not mean that our balance sheet will ultimately shrink by less than it would otherwise, but rather allows us to approach its ultimate level more gradually.</span> <span class="dovish">In particular, slowing the pace of runoff will help ensure a smooth transition, reducing the possibility that money markets experience stress, and thereby facilitating the ongoing decline in our securities holdings that are consistent with reaching the appropriate level of ample reserves.</span></p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">We remain committed to bringing inflation back down to our 2 percent goal and to keeping longer-term inflation expectations well anchored.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Restoring price stability is essential to set the stage for achieving maximum employment and stable prices over the longer run.</span></p>
<p><span class="neutral">To conclude, we understand that our actions affect communities, families, and businesses across the country.</span> <span class="neutral">Everything we do is in service to our public mission.</span> <span class="neutral">We at the Fed will do everything we can to achieve our maximum employment and price stability goals.</span> <span class="neutral">Thank you.</span> <span class="neutral">I look forward to your questions.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Howard.</p>
<p>HOWARD SCHNEIDER. Thank you, Howard Schneider with Reuters. A question and follow-up if I could, do you consider the current policy rate still, are you confident that it's sufficiently restrictive to get inflation back to 2 percent?</p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">CHAIR POWELL. So, I do think the evidence shows pretty clearly that policy is restrictive and is weighing on demand and there are a few places I would point to for that.</span> <span class="hawkish">You can start with the labor market, so demand is still strong, the demand side of the labor market in particular, but it's cooled from its extremely high level of a couple years ago, and you see that in job openings, you saw it, more evidence of that today in the JOLTS report as you'll know.</span> <span class="dovish">It's still higher than pre-pandemic but it has been coming down both in the Indeed Report and the Schultz Report.</span> <span class="hawkish">That's demand cooling.</span> <span class="dovish bold">The same is true of quits and hiring rates, which have essentially normalized.</span> <span class="neutral">I also look at the-- we look at surveys of workers and, pardon me, surveys of workers and businesses and ask workers, "are jobs plentiful?"</span> <span class="neutral">And ask businesses; "are workers plentiful?"</span> <span class="neutral">Is it easy to find workers and you've seen that the answers to those have come back down to pre-pandemic levels.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">You also see in interest-sensitive spending, like housing and investment, you also see that our interest rates are weighing on those activities.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">So, I do think it's clear that policy is restrictive.</span></p>
<p>HOWARD SCHNEIDER. Sufficiently restrictive, I guess.</p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">CHAIR POWELL. So, I would say that we believe it is restrictive and we believe over time it will be sufficiently restrictive.</span> <span class="neutral bold">That will be a question that the data will have to answer.</span></p>
<p>HOWARD SCHNEIDER. So as a follow-up, if inflation continues running roughly sideways as it has been, the job market stays reasonably strong, unemployment low, and expectations are anchored and maintained, would you disrupt that for—</p>
<p>CHAIR POWELL. Expectations are not anchored.</p>
<p>HOWARD SCHNEIDER. Are anchored. Are anchored. Stable, roughly, would you disrupt that for the last half point on PCE?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. I don't want to get into complicated hypotheticals, but I would say that we're committed to retaining our current restrictive stance of policy for as long as is appropriate and we'll do that.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Jeanna.</p>
<p>JEANNA SMIALEK. Thanks for taking our question, Chair Powell. I wonder, obviously Michelle Bowman has been saying that there is a risk that rates may need to increase further, although it's not her baseline outlook, I wonder if you see that as a risk as well, and if so, what change in conditions would merit considering raising rates at this point?</p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">CHAIR POWELL. So I think it's unlikely that the next policy rate move will be a hike.</span> <span class="neutral">I'd say it's unlikely.</span> <span class="neutral">You know, our policy focus is really what I just mentioned, which is how long to keep policy restrictive.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">You ask what would it take, I think we'd need to see persuasive evidence that our policy stance is not sufficiently restrictive to bring inflation sustainably down to 2 percent over time.</span> <span class="neutral">That's not what we think we're seeing, as I mentioned, but something like that is what it would take.</span> <span class="neutral">We'd look at the totality of the data and answer that question that would include inflation, inflation expectations, and all the other data too.</span></p>
<p>JEANNA SMIALEK. Would that be a reacceleration in inflation?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. Well, I think again, the test, what I'm saying is, if we were to come to that conclusion that policy weren't tight enough to achieve that.</span> <span class="neutral">So it would be the totality of all the things we'd be looking at.</span> <span class="neutral">It could be expectations, it could be a combination of things, but if we reach that conclusion and we don't see evidence supporting that conclusion, that's what it would take I think for us to take that step.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Chris.</p>
<p>CHRIS RUGABER. Thank you, Chris Rugaber at Associated Press. You didn't mention the idea that rates are at a peak for the cycle and didn't mention the idea that it might be appropriate to cut rates later this year as you have in previous press conferences. So, has the Fed sort of dropped its easing bias? Where are you standing on that?</p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">So, let me address cuts.</span> <span class="neutral bold">So, obviously our decisions that we make on our policy rate are going to depend on the incoming data, how the outlook is evolving and the balance of risks, as always.</span> <span class="neutral bold">And we'll look at the totality of the data.</span> <span class="neutral bold">So I think, and we think, that policy is well-positioned to address different paths that the economy might take.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">And we've said that we don't think it would be appropriate to dial back our restrictive policy stance until we've gained greater confidence that inflation is moving down sustainably toward 2 percent.</span> <span class="neutral">So, for example, let me take a path; if we did have a path where inflation proves more persistent than expected, and where the labor market remains strong, but inflation is moving sideways and we're not gaining greater confidence, well that would be a case in which it could be appropriate to hold off on rate cuts.</span> <span class="dovish">I think there's also other paths that the economy could take which would cause us to want to consider rate cuts and those would be, two of those paths would be that we do gain greater confidence, as we've said, if that inflation is moving sustainably down to 2 percent and another path could be an unexpected weakening in the labor market, for example.</span> <span class="neutral">So, those are paths in which you could see us cutting rates.</span> <span class="neutral bold">So I think it really will depend on the data.</span> <span class="neutral bold">In terms of peak rate, I think really it's the same question, I think the data will have to answer that question for us.</span></p>
<p>CHRIS RUGABER. And could you just follow on the path where you might not cut, is that you mentioned that would be inflation persistent, I mean, is inflation, would that be the key data in making that decision or could you expand a bit more on that? Thank you.</p>
<p><span class="hawkish bold">CHAIR POWELL. Again, it's, we've set ourselves a test that we, for us to begin to reduce policy restriction, we'd want to be confident that inflation is moving sustainably down to 2 percent, and for sure one of the things we'd be looking at is the performance of inflation.</span> <span class="neutral bold">We'd also be looking at inflation expectations, we'd be looking at the whole story, but clearly, incoming inflation data would be at the very heart of that decision.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Nick.</p>
<p>NICK TIMIRAOS. Nick Timiraos of the Wall Street Journal. Chair Powell, to what extent has the easing in financial conditions since November contributed to the reacceleration in growth, and do you now expect a period of sustained tighter financial conditions will be needed to resume the sort of disinflation the economy saw last year?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So I think it's hard to know that.</span> <span class="neutral">I think we'll be able to look back from down the road and look back and understand it better.</span> <span class="neutral">If you look at -- let's look at growth, really what we've seen so far this year in the first quarter is growth coming in about consistent with where it was last year.</span> <span class="neutral">I know GDP came in lower, but you don't see an acceleration in growth, I mean the thought would be that financial conditions loosened in December and that caused an uptick in activity and that caused inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">Presumably that's what we're tightening in the labor market.</span> <span class="neutral">You don't really see that happening, what you see is economic activity at a level that's roughly the same as last year.</span> <span class="neutral">So, what's causing this inflation, we'll have a better sense of that over time, I don't know that there's an obvious connection there though with easing of financial conditions.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">In terms of tightening, you're right, rates are certainly higher now and have been for some time than they were before the December meeting, and they're higher and that's tighter financial conditions and that's appropriate given what inflation has done in the first quarter.</span></p>
<p>NICK TIMIRAOS. You've said in the past that stronger growth wouldn't necessarily preclude rate cuts. I wonder would continued strength in the labor market change your view about the appropriate stance of policy if it was accompanied by signs the wage growth was reaccelerating.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So, I just want to be careful that we don't target wage growth or the labor market and remember what we saw last year; very strong growth, a really tight labor market, and historically fast decline in inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">So, and that's because we know there are two forces at work here.</span> <span class="neutral">There's the unwinding of the pandemic related supply side distortions and demand side distortions, and there's also monetary policy, restrictive monetary policy.</span> <span class="neutral">So, I wouldn't rule out that something like that can continue, I wouldn't give up at this point on further things happening on the supply side either because we do see that companies still report that there are supply side issues that they're facing, and also even when the supply side issues are solved it should take some time for that to affect economic activity and ultimately inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">So there are still those things.</span> <span class="neutral">So I don't like to say that either growth or a strong labor market in and of itself would automatically create problems on inflation, because of course it didn't do that last year.</span> <span class="neutral">You ask about wages, we also don't, we don't target wages, we target price inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">It is one of the inputs, the point with wages is of course we, like everyone else, like to see high wages, but we also want to see them not eaten up by high inflation, and that's really what we're trying to do is to cool the economy and work with what's happening on the supply side to bring the economy back to 2 percent inflation.</span> <span class="hawkish">Part of that will probably be having wage increases move down incrementally toward levels that are more sustainable.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Rachel.</p>
<p>RACHEL SIEGEL. Hi, Chair Powell, Rachel Siegel from the Washington Post. Thanks for taking our questions. You talked about needing time to gain more confidence that inflation is sustainably moving back down to 2 percent, it's May now, do you have time this year to cut three times, just given the calendar?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. Yeah, I'm never really thinking of it that way.</span> <span class="hawkish">What we said is that we need to be more confident and we've said, my colleagues and I today said that we didn't see progress in the first quarter and I've said that it appears then that it's going to take longer for us to reach that point of confidence, so I don't know how long it'll take, I can just say that when we get that confidence, then rate cuts will be in scope and I don't know exactly when that will be.</span></p>
<p>RACHEL SIEGEL. And with hindsight, are there any signs that you can look back on now, looking at the reports from January or February or March, that suggested something more worrying than just expected bumpiness?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. Not really, what-- so I thought it was appropriate to reserve judgment until we had the full quarter's data, until we saw the March data.</span> <span class="hawkish">And so take a step back, what do we now see in the first quarter? We see strong economic activity, we see a strong labor market, and we see inflation.</span> <span class="hawkish">We see three inflation readings and so I think you're at a point there where you should take some signal.</span> <span class="neutral">We don't like to react to one or two month's data, but this is a full quarter and I think it's appropriate to take signal now, and we are taking signal.</span> <span class="hawkish">And the signal that we're taking is that it's likely to take longer for us to gain confidence that we are on a sustainable path down to 2 percent inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">That's the signal that we're taking now, yeah.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Steve.</p>
<p>STEVE LIESMAN. Mr. Chair, if I could-- Steve Liesman, CNBC. If I could follow-up on that; what particular areas were sort of temporary or blips in the inflation data in the first quarter? What's the dynamic by which you expect them to work out in the coming months and quarters?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So we will, we have put the thing under a microscope.</span> <span class="neutral">I will say nothing is going to come out to that that's going to change the view I think, that in fact we didn't gain confidence and that it's going to take longer to get that confidence.</span> <span class="neutral">But, confidence.</span> <span class="neutral">I just think, you know the story, what's happened since December as you've seen, higher goods inflation than expected and you've seen higher non-housing services inflation than expected and those two are working together to sort of be higher than we had thought.</span> <span class="neutral">And there are stories behind how that happened, and we, I think my expectation is that we will over the course of this year, see inflation move back down.</span> <span class="hawkish">That's my forecast, I think my confidence in that is lower than it was because of the data that we've seen.</span> <span class="neutral">So we're looking at those things, we also continue to expect, and I continue to expect that housing services inflation, given where market rents are, those will show up in measured housing services inflation over time.</span> <span class="neutral">We believe then it will, it just, it looks like the lag, that there are substantial lags between when lower market rates turned up and for new tenants and when it shows up for existing tenants or for in-housing services.</span></p>
<p>STEVE LIESMAN. If I could just follow-up. Is there a bit of a contradiction in the idea that you are reducing quantitative tightening, which is sort of an easing, while you're holding rates steady at a restrictive rate to try to slow and cool the economy and inflation? Thank you.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. I wouldn't say that, no, I mean the active tool of monetary policy is of course the interest rates and this is a long, a plan we've long had in place to slow, really not in order to provide accommodation to the economy but to, or to be less restrictive to the economy, it really is to ensure that the process of shrinking the balance sheet down to where we want to get it is a smooth one and doesn't wind up with financial market turmoil the way it did the last time we did this and the only other time we've ever done this.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Craig.</p>
<p>CRAIG TORRES. Craig Torres from Bloomberg. Two questions, first simple one; given the run of data since March, has the probability in your mind of no cuts this year increased or stayed the same? That's the first question. Second question; Chair Powell, you joined the Board in 2012, and I'm sure you remember as I do, what the jobless recovery was like, lawyers, accountants, all kinds of highly qualified people who couldn't get jobs. And given your history there, I wonder if there's an argument for being more patient with inflation here. We have strong productivity growth that's helping wages grow up, go up, we have good employment, and so it seems to me there's a lot of hysteria about inflation. I agree, nobody likes it, but is there an argument for being patient and working with the economic cycle to get it down over time? Thank you.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So on your first question, I don't have a probability estimate for you.</span> <span class="hawkish">But all I can say is that we've said that we didn't think it would be appropriate to cut until we were more confident that inflation was moving sustainably down to 2 percent, we didn't get our confidence in that didn't increase in the first quarter and in fact, what really happened was we came to the view that it will take longer to get that confidence.</span> <span class="neutral">And I think there are, I think the economy has been very hard for forecasters broadly to predict its path, but there are paths to not cutting and there are paths to cutting, it's really going to depend on the data.</span> <span class="neutral">In terms of the employment mandate, to your point, if you go back a couple of years, our sort of framework document says that when you look at the two mandate goals, and if one of them is further away from goal than the other, then you focus on that one.</span> <span class="neutral">You actually, it's the time to get back there, times how far it is from the goal.</span> <span class="hawkish">And that was clearly inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">So, our focus was very much on inflation.</span> <span class="dovish">As, and this is what we referred to in the statement, as inflation has come down, now to below 3 percent on a 12-month basis, it's become, we're now focusing the other goal, the employment goal now comes back into focus.</span> <span class="dovish">And so we are focusing on it.</span> <span class="neutral">And that's how we think about that.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Claire.</p>
<p>CLAIRE JONES. Claire Jones, Financial Times. Thanks a lot for the opportunity to ask the questions. Just to go back to the answer before the previous one, it seemed to suggest that you think the likeliest path of inflation is one that's going to allow you to have a situation where rates are lower at the end of the year than they are right now. It'd be good if you could just confirm whether or not that's a correct reading. And the key one, GDP print is led some to start mentioning the term stagflation with respect to the U.S. economy. Do you or anyone else on the FOMC think this is now a risk? Thank you.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. Yeah, I'm not dealing really in likelihoods.</span> <span class="neutral">I think there are paths that the economy can take that would involve cuts and there are paths that wouldn't and I don't have great confidence in which of those paths, I think, I would say my personal forecast is that we will begin to see further progress on inflation this year.</span> <span class="neutral">I don't know that it will be enough, sufficient, I don't know that it won't.</span> <span class="neutral">I think we're going to have to let the data lead us on that.</span> <span class="neutral">In terms of your question, your second question was stagflation.</span> <span class="dovish">I guess I would say, I was around for stagflation and it was 10 percent unemployment, it was high single digits inflation, right now we have-- and very slow growth, so right now we have 3 percent growth, which is pretty solid growth I would say, by any measure, and we have inflation running under 3 percent.</span> <span class="neutral">So, I don't really understand where that's coming from.</span> <span class="neutral">And in addition, I would say most forecasters, including our forecasting, was that last year's level of growth was very high, 3.4 percent in I guess the fourth quarter, and probably not going to be sustained and would come down.</span> <span class="neutral">But that would be our forecast.</span> <span class="neutral">That wouldn't be stagflation.</span> <span class="neutral">That would still be to a very healthy level of growth.</span> <span class="dovish">And of course with inflation, we will return inflation to 2 percent and that won't be, so I don't see the stag or the flation actually.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Michael McKee.</p>
<p>MICHAEL MCKEE. Michael McKee from Bloomberg Radio and Television. The Vice Chair of the FOMC said recently that he's willing to consider the idea that potential growth has moved up and of course he's Mr. Potential Growth r star. Do you share that view and would that imply that maybe policy isn't tight enough?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So I think I would take that question this way; we saw a year of very high productivity growth in 2023, and we saw a year of I think negative productivity growth in 2022, so I think it's hard to draw from the data, I mean the question is will productivity run-- there are two questions, one is will productivity run persistently above its longer run trend?</span> <span class="neutral">I don't think we know that.</span> <span class="neutral">In terms of potential output though, that's a separate question, we've had a, what amounts to a significant increase in the potential output of the economy that's not about productivity it was about having more labor, frankly, both in 2022, both for participation also through immigration.</span> <span class="neutral">So, we're very much like other forecasters and economists, getting our arms around what that means for potential output this year and next year and last year for that matter too.</span> <span class="neutral">So, I think in that case I think you really do have a significant increase in potential output, but you've also got, so you've got more supply, but those people also come in, they work, they have jobs, they spend, so you've also got demand.</span> <span class="neutral">So there may be, it may be that you get more supply than you get demand at the beginning, but ultimately it should be neither inflationary nor disinflationary over a longer period.</span></p>
<p>MICHAEL MCKEE. You said earlier that at this point you're not really considering rate increases. If growth is higher but you're not considering rate increases, does that imply that you're more worried about causing the economy to slow too much than you are about inflation taking off again?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. No, I think we believe our policy stance is in a good place and is appropriate to the current situation.</span> <span class="hawkish">We believe it's restrictive, and our evidence for that I went over earlier, you see it in the labor market, you see it in inflation sensitive spending, where demand has clearly come down a lot over the past few years.</span> <span class="neutral">And that's more from monetary policy, whereas the supply side things that are happening are more on the supply side.</span> <span class="neutral">So, that's how I would think about it.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Edward.</p>
<p>EDWARD LAWRENCE. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Edward Lawrence from FOX Business. So, GDP growth is about 2 percent, employment is about 4 percent, it feels a lot like a steady state and we have 3 percent inflation so if the data remains the same that you're seeing, and I know you said you don't see a rate hike, but it stands to reason that you would need a rate hike to get from 3 to 2 percent inflation. So was there any discussion about a rate hike in today's meeting and are you satisfied with 3 percent inflation for the rest of the year?</p>
<p><span class="hawkish">CHAIR POWELL. Well, of course we're not satisfied with 3 percent inflation.</span> <span class="hawkish">Three percent can't be in a sentence with satisfied.</span> <span class="hawkish">So, we will return inflation to 2 percent over time, but over time.</span> <span class="neutral">And we think our policy stance is appropriate to do that.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">So if we were to conclude that policy is not sufficiently restrictive to bring inflation sustainably down to 2 percent, then that would be what it would take for us to want to increase rates.</span> <span class="neutral">We don't see that, we don't see evidence for that.</span> <span class="neutral">So that's where we are.</span></p>
<p>EDWARD LARENCE. Was there discussion about a rate hike at all?</p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">CHAIR POWELL. So the policy focus has been on, has really been on what to do about holding the current level of restriction.</span> <span class="neutral">That's really, that's part of the policy, that's where the policy discussion was in the meeting.</span></p>
<p>EDWARD LAWRENCE. I wanted to follow on the 3 percent, is there a time frame of persistent inflation that would trigger a rate hike?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. There isn't any rule, you can't look to a rule, these are going to be judgment calls.</span> <span class="hawkish">Clearly restrictive monetary policy needs more time to do its job.</span> <span class="neutral">That is pretty clear based on what we're seeing, how long that will take and how patient we should be is going to depend on the totality of the data, how the outlook evolves.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Victoria.</p>
<p>VICTORIA GUIDA. Hi, Victoria Guida with Politico. You've talked about your commitment to being apolitical and nonpartisan, and I was just wondering given that it's an election year, is the bar for rate changes higher close to an election, and similarly, is there a significant economic difference between starting to cut in say September versus December?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So we're always going to do what we think the right thing for the economy is when we come to that consensus view that it's the right thing to do for the economy.</span> <span class="neutral">That's our record, that's what we do.</span> <span class="neutral">We're not looking at anything else, it's hard enough to get the economics right here.</span> <span class="neutral">These are difficult things and if we were to take on a whole nother set of factors and use that as a new filter, it would reduce the likelihood we'd actually get the economics right.</span> <span class="neutral">So that's how we think about it around here.</span> <span class="neutral">And you know we're at peace over it.</span> <span class="neutral">We know that we'll do what we think is the right thing, when we think it's the right thing, and we'll all do that.</span> <span class="neutral">And that's how everybody around here thinks.</span> <span class="neutral">So I can't say it enough, that we just don't, we just don't go down that road.</span> <span class="neutral">If you go down that road, where do you stop?</span> <span class="neutral">And so we're not on that road, we're on the road where we're serving all the American people and making our decisions based on the data and how those data affect the outlook and the balance of risks.</span></p>
<p>VICTORIA GUIDA. And then, is there a significant difference between whether you start in say September versus December, an economic difference.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. There's a significant difference between an institution that takes into account all sorts of political events and one that doesn't.</span> <span class="neutral">That's where the significant difference is, and we just don't do that.</span> <span class="neutral">I mean you can go back and read the transcripts for every-- this is my fourth election, fourth presidential election here, read all the transcripts and see if anybody mentions in any way, the pending election.</span> <span class="neutral">It just isn't part of our thinking.</span> <span class="neutral">It's not what we're hired to do.</span> <span class="neutral">If we start down that road, again, I don't know how you stop.</span> <span class="neutral">So.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Simon.</p>
<p>SIMON RABINOVITCH. Hi, thank you Chair Powell. Question about the labor market; you've mentioned a few times that the labor market is normalizing, certainly today's JOLTS data suggested that things are kind of getting back to pre-pandemic levels. One thing that hasn't normalized is wage growth, which is still quite a bit stronger than before the pandemic. I wonder if you can share your analysis of why that's happening. Is it a lagging indicator, or is something else going on?</p>
<p><span class="neutral bold">CHAIR POWELL. So I think if you go back to where wages peaked, wage increases peaked, a couple three years ago, essentially all wage measures have come down substantially to that.</span> <span class="hawkish">But, they are not down to where they were before the pandemic.</span> <span class="hawkish">They're still roughly a percentage point higher.</span> <span class="dovish">And we've seen pretty consistent progress, but not uniformly, and you'll note the ECI reading from Tuesday was, it was expected to be, to have come down and essentially it was flat year over year to I think roughly, so yeah, I mean that part of it is bumpy and again, we don't target wage increases, but in the longer run if you have wage increases running higher than productivity would warrant, and then there will be inflationary pressures.</span> <span class="neutral">Employers will raise prices over time if that's the case, so we've seen progress, it's been inconsistent, but we have seen a substantial decline overall but we have a ways to go on that.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Scott. Nancy. I'm sorry.</p>
<p>NANCY MARSHALL-GENZER. Hey Chair Powell, Nancy Marshall-Genzer from Marketplace. You mentioned consumers and consumers are feeling the weight of interest rates right now. Mortgage rates are up as are rates for car loans, credit cards, people looking to borrow are very discouraged, that's reflected in their views on the economy. What would you say to them?</p>
<p><span class="dovish">CHAIR POWELL. Well, the thing that hurts everybody and particularly people in the lower income brackets is inflation.</span> <span class="dovish">If you're a person who's living paycheck to paycheck, and suddenly all the things you buy, the fundamentals of life, go up in price, you are in trouble right away.</span> <span class="hawkish">And so, with those people in mind in particular, what we're doing is we're using our tools to bring down inflation.</span> <span class="neutral">It will take some time, but we will succeed and we will bring inflation back down to 2 percent and then people won't have to worry about it again.</span> <span class="neutral">That's what we're doing, and we know that it's painful and inconvenient but the dividends will be paid, will be very large and everyone will share in those dividends and we've made quite a lot of progress if you can think about it.</span> <span class="dovish">I think headline, core PCE peaked at 5.8, now it's at-- anyway, headline peaked at 7.1, now it's at 2.7.</span> <span class="neutral">Don't want to get that wrong.</span></p>
<p>NANCY MARSHALL-GENZER. No, you don't. Quick follow-up; are current interest rates really doing that much though to fight inflation right now for those consumers?</p>
<p><span class="hawkish">CHAIR POWELL. Yes, I mean I think that restrictive monetary policy is doing what it's supposed to do, and but it's also in this case unusually working alongside and with the healing of the supply side.</span> <span class="neutral">What was different this time was that a big part of the source of the inflation and the reason why we're having this conversation is that we had this supply side kind of collapse with shortages and bottlenecks and all that kind of thing.</span> <span class="neutral">And so, and this was to do with the shutting down and reopening of the economy and other things that really raised demand.</span> <span class="neutral">So, many factors did that.</span> <span class="dovish">So, I think now you see those two things working together, the reversal of those supply and demand distortions from the pandemic and the response to it, along with restrictive monetary policy, those two things are working to bring down inflation and we've made a lot of progress.</span> <span class="dovish">Let's remember how far we've come.</span> <span class="hawkish">And we have a ways to go, we've got work left to do, but we're not looking at the very high inflation rates that we were seeing two years ago.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Courtenay.</p>
<p>COURTENAY BROWN. Courtenay Brown from Axios. Thanks for taking our questions, Chair Powell. I wanted to follow-up on something you mentioned earlier on housing inflation, there's kind of been this long awaited disinflation and shelter that still hasn't arrived. So I guess two questions, how do you explain the substantial lags between some of the private sector data we're seeing and the government data, and how confident are you that rents will be helpful in the inflation front in the coming months?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So essentially there are a number of places in the economy where there are just lag structures built into the inflation process and housing is one of them.</span> <span class="neutral">So, when you have-- when someone goes to, a new person goes to rent an apartment, that's called market rent and you can see market rents are barely going up at all.</span> <span class="neutral">The inflation in those has been very low.</span> <span class="neutral">But it takes, before that they were incredibly high, they sort of led the high part.</span> <span class="neutral">So what happens is those market rents take years actually to get all the way into rents for tenants who are rolling over their leases.</span> <span class="neutral">Landlords don't tend to charge as much of an increase to a rollover tenant for whatever reason, and what that does is it builds up a sort of an unrealized portion of increases when there have been big increases and what happens is, and it's complicated but the story is it just takes some time for that to get in.</span> <span class="hawkish">Now, I am confident that as long as market rents remain low, this is going to show up in measured inflation, assuming that market rents do remain low.</span> <span class="neutral">What will be the exact timing of it?</span> <span class="neutral">I think we've learned that the lags are longer, we now think significantly longer than we thought at the beginning, and so confident that it will come but not so confident in the timing of it.</span> <span class="dovish">But yes, I expect that this will happen.</span></p>
<p>COURTENAY BROWN. Thanks.</p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Nick Jasinski.</p>
<p>NICHOLAS JASINSKI. Thank you Chair Powell, for taking the questions. This is Nicholas Jasinski from Barron's Magazine. It seems that over the past three or four years economies and central banks in developed markets at least have been on more or less the same trajectory, easing during the pandemic, fighting inflation with restrictive policy on the way out, feels like that may be ending in 2024 based on some of the economic data from Europe and the U.S. and Japan and statements from those central banks as well. So my question is, what considerations or risks does a period of more divergent global economic trajectories and central bank policies present for the FOMC?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So, you're right, I think that may happen and we all serve domestic mandates, right?</span> <span class="neutral">So I think the difference between the United States and other countries that are now considering rate cuts is that they're just not having the kind of growth we're having.</span> <span class="neutral">They have, their inflation is performing about like ours or maybe a little better, but they're not experiencing the kind of growth we're experiencing.</span> <span class="neutral">So, we actually have the luxury of having strong growth in a strong labor market, very low unemployment, high job creation, and all of that and we can be patient and we'll be careful and cautious as we approach the decision to cut rates.</span> <span class="neutral">Whereas I think other jurisdictions may go before that.</span> <span class="neutral">In terms of the implications, I think obviously markets see it coming, it's priced in now, and so I think the markets and economies can adapt to it and I think we haven't seen in addition for the emerging market economies, we haven't seen the kind of turmoil that was more frequent 20 years ago, 30 years ago, and that's I think partly because emerging market countries, many of them have much better monetary policy frameworks, much more credibility on inflation and so they're navigating this pretty well this time.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Jennifer.</p>
<p>JENNIFER SCHONBERGER. Thank you Chair Powell, Jennifer Schonberger with Yahoo Finance. You sort of backed away from the notion that the economy would need to encounter pain for inflation to come back down. But given the sticky inflation data in the first quarter, can disinflation still happen along relatively painless path for the economy or is some softening in the labor market and the economy likely needed to bring inflation back down?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So you're right, I think we thought, and most people thought, there would have to be probably significant dislocations somewhere in the economy, perhaps the labor market, to get inflation all the way down from the very high levels it was at at the beginning of this episode.</span> <span class="dovish">That didn't happen, that's a tremendous result, we're very of course gratified and pleased that hasn't happened.</span> <span class="neutral">And if you look at the dynamics that enabled that, it really was this empty, that so much of the gain was from the unwinding of things that weren't to do with monetary policy, with the unwinding of the distortions to the economy, supply problems, supply side problems and also some demand issues as well.</span> <span class="dovish">The unwinding of those really helped inflation come down.</span> <span class="neutral">Now, as I've said, I'm not giving up on that.</span> <span class="dovish">So I think it is possible that those forces will still work to help us bring inflation down.</span> <span class="hawkish">We can't be guaranteed that that's true though.</span> <span class="neutral">And so we're trying to use our tools in a way that keeps the labor market strong and the economy strong, but also helps bring inflation back down to 2 percent sustainably.</span> <span class="hawkish">We will bring inflation down to 2 percent sustainably, we hope we can do it without significant dislocations in the labor market or elsewhere.</span></p>
<p>JENNIFER SCHONBERGER. And speaking of dislocations in the labor market, in terms of cutting you said if there were weakness in the job market that could be a reason to cut rates. So if the unemployment rate were to tick above 4 percent but inflation not back down to your 2 percent target, how would you look at that? Would the unemployment rate popping back above 4 percent catch your attention?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. You know, I said an unexpected weakening is the way I characterize it.</span> <span class="neutral">So, and I'm not going to try to define exactly what I mean by that.</span> <span class="neutral">But, it would be, it would have to be meaningful and get our attention and lead us to think that the labor market was really significantly weakening for us to want to react to it.</span> <span class="neutral">A couple of tenths in the unemployment rate would be, would probably not do that, but a broader, it would be a broader thing that would suggest that it would be appropriate to consider cutting.</span> <span class="neutral">I think whether you decide to cut will depend on all the facts and circumstances, not just that one.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Kyle.</p>
<p>KYLE CAMPBELL. Chair Powell, thanks for taking the question. Kyle Campbell with American Banker. You've said that broad and material changes are needed for the Basel III endgame proposal and you've mentioned that a re-proposal is something that's on the table. As you've had more time to sort of sit with the public commentary, process that, and understand the options available to you, do you have a better sense of whether a re-proposal will be necessary, and do you have a timeline in mind for when some sort of movement will be made on that front, either a re-proposal or a move to finalize?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So let me start by saying that the Fed is committed to completing this process and carrying out Basel III endgame in a way that's faithful to Basel and also comparable to what the other large comparable jurisdictions are doing.</span> <span class="neutral">We haven't made any decisions on policy or on process at all, nothing, no decisions have been made.</span> <span class="neutral">I'll say again though, if we conclude that re-proposal is appropriate, we won't hesitate to insist on that.</span></p>
<p>KYLE CAMPBELL. And then do you need to resolve issues with the capital proposal in order to advance other parts of the regulatory agenda or do you expect to continue to make progress on those other agenda items?</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. You know there's no mechanical rule in place there, but I would say that the Basel III process is by far the most important thing and really is I think occupying us at this time in terms of what's,what we're moving ahead with.</span></p>
<p>MICHELLE SMITH. Let's go to Mark for the last question.</p>
<p>MARK HAMRICK. Thank you, Mark Hamrick with Bankrate. Mr. Chairman, what can you tell us about the approach that you take with your role on the sense of trying to achieve consensus, what you recently identified as a priority, while allowing for a range of views or even dissent. We don't see many dissenting votes in the official statements, even when more spirited discussions are noted in the minutes after the fact. How do you avoid groupthink and avoid a higher risk of a policy mistake? Thank you.</p>
<p><span class="neutral">CHAIR POWELL. So I think if you listen to, and you all do, listen to my 18 colleagues on the FOMC, you'll see that we do not lack for a diversity of voices and perspectives.</span> <span class="neutral">We really don't.</span> <span class="neutral">And it's one of the great aspects of the Federal Reserve System.</span> <span class="neutral">We have 12 reserve banks around the country where they have their own economic staff, not the people who work here at the Board, there are different people and so each reserve bank has its own culture around monetary policy and its own approach and that kind of thing.</span> <span class="neutral">It guarantees you a diversity of perspectives.</span> <span class="neutral">So, I think perspectives are very diverse but, and in terms of dissents, we have dissents and a thoughtful dissent is a good thing, if someone really makes you think, that kind of thing.</span> <span class="neutral">But all I can say from my standpoint is I try, I listen carefully to people, I try to incorporate their thinking, or do everything I can to incorporate their thinking into what we're doing, and I think many people if they feel that's happening, that for most people most of the time, that'll be enough and but I'm not, I mean it's not frowned upon or illegal or against the rules or anything like that.</span> <span class="neutral">It just is the way things come out and I mean I think we have a very diverse group, frankly more diverse than it used to be in many dimensions, more diverse from the obvious gender and demographic ways, but also we have more people who are not PhD economists so we have people from business and law and academia, and things like that.</span> <span class="neutral">So I think we actually do have quite a good diverse perspective.</span> <span class="neutral">I think all of us read these stories about the lack of diversity and we look around the room and say, I don't understand, I really don't understand what they're talking about.</span> <span class="neutral">So, but I get the question though.</span> <span class="neutral">Thank you very much.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Presser" /><category term="policy" /><category term="QT" /><category term="Powell" /><category term="FOMC" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Barkin Emphasizes Need for Restrictive Rates to Tame Stubborn Inflation</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/barkin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barkin Emphasizes Need for Restrictive Rates to Tame Stubborn Inflation" /><published>2024-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/barkin</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/barkin.html"><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.</p>

<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<div id="youtube-player-container"></div>

<!-- Load the IFrame Player API code asynchronously -->
<script src="https://www.youtube.com/iframe_api"></script>

<script>
  var player;
  function onYouTubeIframeAPIReady() {
    player = new YT.Player('youtube-player-container', {
      height: '315',
      width: '560',
      videoId: 'UnZ-F_TNgNM'
    });
  };

function seekToTime(timestamp) {
  var timeArr = timestamp.split(":");
  var hours = 0;
  var minutes = 0;
  var seconds = 0;

  // Check if the timestamp includes hours
  if (timeArr.length === 3) {
    hours = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[2], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 2) {
    // If the timestamp is only minutes and seconds
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 1) {
    // If the timestamp is only seconds
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
  }

  // Calculate total seconds
  var totalSeconds = hours * 3600 + minutes * 60 + seconds;

  // Seek to the specified time if possible
  if (player && player.seekTo) {
    player.seekTo(totalSeconds, true);
  }
}


// Attach click event listeners to each sentence
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function() {
  document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(span) {
    span.addEventListener("click", function() {
      // Remove highlighting/underscore from all spans
      document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(otherSpan) {
        otherSpan.classList.remove("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      });
      
      // Add highlighting/underscore to the clicked span
      this.classList.add("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      
      // Seek the video to the timestamp
      var timestamp = this.getAttribute("data-timestamp");
      seekToTime(timestamp);
    });
  });
});

</script>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><span id="sentence-1" data-timestamp="00:03" class="neutral">Bloomberg Audio Studios podcasts radio News. Hello and welcome to another episode of the Odd Lots podcast. I'm Tracy Alloway and I'm Joe Weisenthal. So Joe, we have a treat for all Odd Lots listeners. That's right, we have a special episode of the podcast with Richmond Fed president Tom Barkin. So we were actually on a reporting trip shadowing Tom as he goes through some of his district and speaks to local business leaders there. We learned a lot. We spent a lot of time with him. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-2" data-timestamp="00:50" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>You'll hear more from that trip in an upcoming Odd Lots episode, but in the meantime, we also talked to him about some more macro trends - things that are happening right now that he's seeing in the economy. And we're going to share that portion of the interview with you right now. So so far in 2024, we've seen three - hotter than generally, the inflation data has been hotter than expected. And some of the, uh, there's certainly been some cold water on some of the soft landing optimism. What do you attribute that to? Do you think this is a new trend or is it a speed bump in the road, as they say?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-3" data-timestamp="01:27" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b>Well, so I think there are two interesting things going on with the data. One is demand has been pretty robust against most expectations that it would slow, slow down. We got retail sales this week, very strong. We've got three strong job reports this year. And so the economy in general still seems to be very healthy. And I think a lot of people wondered whether, you know, we weren't at the end of a growth period - seems, still seems to be strong.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-4" data-timestamp="01:52" class="hawkish bold">At the same time, inflation has remained stubbornly above 3%, you know, on a monthly annualized rate. And there are lots of ways to interpret it. I am from the school that no one's as good as they are on their best day or as bad as they are on their worst. The seven months before the end of the year, we ran at 1.9% headline inflation.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-5" data-timestamp="02:12" class="dovish">The last three months have been somewhat higher. If you took the 10-month number, it's not that bad actually. And so I think the overall story - that inflation's moderating - is still the right story. But I've been of the view that inflation has been, will be more stubborn to come back to 2% than we would like. And in particular, in the last half of last year, part of the reason the numbers came back so nicely was that goods turned deflationary, and that offset still higher than normal levels of inflation on services and shelter.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-6" data-timestamp="02:46" class="hawkish">We're not trying to pick a particular mix of inflation, but it did make me worry that if goods price reductions ceased, you'd still be left with higher than normal services and shelter. And that's what's happened in the first quarter of the year. Is there still room for goods to reduce? Of course. Is there still a story of why shelter might come down, with new rents coming down? Of course. And with wages normalizing services, absolutely. But it hasn't happened yet.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-7" data-timestamp="03:17" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>On this note, the last time we spoke to you on the podcast, you talked about the need to maybe offset housing strength in a different area. So if housing has proved to be surprisingly resilient, maybe you need to see an offset somewhere else in the economy. Is that still your thinking? </span></p>

<p><b>Tom Barkin: </b><span id="sentence-8" data-timestamp="03:35" class="hawkish bold">Well, I'm open to housing coming down. And there are folks who've done models that suggest that with new rents coming down the way they have, we're just minutes away from shelter inflation coming down as well. And that would be great. If it doesn't come down and you want to get to 2%, then either goods or services or both need to run at less than their historic levels of inflation. That's just simple, simple math. And if it doesn't come down, that's what you'd be looking for - is some sense that relative prices have changed in way. And I, and I want to make this point, that that's entirely conceivable. Relative prices change all the time. In the 2000s, we had healthcare inflation that was quite significant, and much more than it was in the 90s. But goods price deflation came down. So the basket does shift, and it's fine if it shifts. Just needs to get to 2% overall.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-9" data-timestamp="04:20" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>There's sort of whispers out there, and some people talk about it, and you can kind of see it in the rates options markets and stuff. But there is this talk, like, what if the hiking cycle isn't actually over? What if the next rate move is not a cut, as has been, uh, the presumption for a while? What do you think it would have to take, or what would you have to see in the data to say, "No, this isn't just a matter of waiting for the improvement to occur. There is a reason to do more work."</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="04:47" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b> It would have to be around inflation reaccelerating. And you know, having conviction that you need to do more work. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="04:55" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>When - like, I mean, okay, so we've had this little 3-month pickup from the previous s months. What is, like, okay, this is actually inflation reaccelerating rather than just a durable trend versus a blip? Yeah, what does that look like? What is - they - what - well, put - no, I'm, I'm going to say, what is the durable, what constitutes a durable trend? </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-11" data-timestamp="05:16" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b>I mean, a trend that is durable. I think it's really hard to get into hypotheticals here. You know, what I'll say is we're in a situation today where demand is robust, but I see no signs yet that it's overheating. And overheating would lead to pressure on wages, would lead to pressure on prices such that things were escalating. And you can't find that in the wage numbers, or even in the three-month price numbers. And you can't find that. So you know, demand is robust but not overheating. And inflation is - has come down and is still coming down on a 12-month basis, but is stubbornly, you know, at least over the last three months, plateaued above our target. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-12" data-timestamp="05:49" class="hawkish">And so I think that makes policy pretty straightforward with today's world, which is, is you have restrictive rates, and you want to be restrictive and bring inflation down. You can come up with scenarios where those - the two parts of our mandate - are in different balance. But right now, I think you've got healthy but not overheated demand, and you've got inflation that remains stubbornly high. So I think, to me, the policy path is pretty straightforward. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-13" data-timestamp="06:20" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>I think you anticipated my next question. But you say rates are restrictive. How are you judging the restrictiveness of monetary policy? Because when I look at something like the Financial Conditions Index, up until the past week or so, or even few days, it was pretty loose. And so there seems to be a disconnect between a certain number of Fed officials who will say policy is restrictive versus looking at something like that Financial Conditions Index, or even the amount of refinancing being undertaken by, like, the corporate bond market or the loan market recently.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-14" data-timestamp="06:49" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin:</b> Right, so there are many financial conditions indices. Some of them show looser than others. The ones that seem to show the loosest are the ones that put the most weight on the equity markets, obviously, we were with our carport manufacturer today. He would certainly say financial conditions are tight. And you know, it's very clear to me, as I talk around the economy, that there are significant sectors where financial conditions are tight. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-15" data-timestamp="07:17" class="dovish">And they do tend to be those sectors like this guy who's most, uh, vulnerable to construction and to home, right, and people spending around their home. And in his case, RV garage covers are a big part of what he does. And of course, RVs went crazy, but people aren't buying RVs at the same pace anymore. So I do see interest rates going to the economy, and I see that as - but I also think it's fair to say the level of restrictiveness is something you take at some faith. I do like to look at real TIPS yields to give me some sense. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-16" data-timestamp="07:47" class="neutral">But you are comparing it to a hypothetical - not hypothetical, a estimated R-star - that is hard to know where you really are. And there are lots of estimates, including one from the Richmond Fed, that are higher than most people's R-star. So you have to be open to the notion that the level of restrictiveness is less than you think. And you would learn that through the economy. You learn that through demand accelerating more than you'd think it would. And that's something you have to be attentive to.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="08:14" class="neutral">I haven't yet concluded that the - overheating would be - that would be part of your case for doing more, would be overheating. So you don't think it's - you're as restrictive as you thought you were, which meant you have to do a little more. 
  
<p><span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="08:22" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>I just have one more question. But when it comes to, you know, housing, obviously, just - you know, it's a big driver of the upward pressure on inflation through various measures. It's also sort of this major societal problem that people are frustrated with almost across the country. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-18" data-timestamp="08:39" class="neutral">When you're thinking about rate policy, how much, like, do you think about not just, okay, what's going to happen in the next three months or whatever, but how much does restrictive policy today restrain the housing supply of tomorrow? Whether it's like - a multifamily - we got recent numbers that new multifamily development is really fallen off quite a bit. And in theory, that means housing - more, more scarcity in 2026, whatever. Do you fold that into your thinking in terms of policy today?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-19" data-timestamp="09:08" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b>You try to think it through as best you can. Don't forget that the impact of higher rates on housing demand is pretty immediate. And the impact of higher rates on housing supply, because it gets delivered two years later, is more further out. And when we started raising rates, we were in the middle of as frothy a period in the housing market as I remember 12 bids per house, houses going for $40,000 over list. And so low rates wasn't the answer to that particular supply and demand issue. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-20" data-timestamp="09:40" class="neutral">I think this theory of the case is that you raise rates, it brings down demand to levels more in balance with supply. And while it may have an impact with supply, you get inflation under control, and then you can lower rates again so that supply can blossom. I think that's the theory of the case. I'll point out that in this - I mean, you mentioned multifamily, but single-family starts quite strong and much stronger than normal in this cycle, in part because I think availability of existing homes has been so low. And multifamily starts have come down a bunch, but that was from a very, very high peak. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="10:11" class="neutral">And so they're not that far off today where they were before the pandemic. And so we're - stuff's still getting built, there is a future potential challenge in supply. But I think the hope is that, you know, demand comes off enough that we can bring that market into better balance. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="10:43" class="neutral"><b>Q: </b>Just going back to the inflation outlook, I think at this point there have been a number of Fed officials who seem to have suggested that the worst outcome of the current monetary policy cycle, or one of the worst outcomes, would be if they decided to start easing, only to see inflation pick back up again. And I guess my question is, why - why is that so bad? Because couldn't you just alter course? Couldn't you start tightening again if you saw that in the data? </span></p>
  
<p><b>Tom barkin: </b><span id="sentence-22" data-timestamp="11:16" class="neutral">Well, I think it's hard to do my job and not be aware of the 70s. And I remember the 70s, it wasn't pretty. I also had bad hair in that, in that era. But what happened in the 70s - this is the fundamental object lesson of monetary policy - is every time there was the slightest hint that the economy could be turning down, they lowered rates.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-23" data-timestamp="11:34" class="hawkish bold">And then inflation came back up. And then they increased rates. And the issue is, when the Fed doesn't look like it's resolute on inflation, inflation doesn't come back to where it was before. It comes to higher than it was before, which means that every time to fight it, you've got to take rates even higher, which means that the damage you do to the economy is even more. And so letting expectations spiral out of control, I think, is just a very risky thing for the economy. </span><span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="12:01" class="hawkish">And that's not some theoretical model. We actually lived it in the 70s. And, and much like me, the 70s weren't pretty. </span></p>
  
<p><b>Q: </b><span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="12:10" class="neutral">Just 'cause you mentioned R-star and the neutral rate. And I get the sense - and this is just based off of a Bank for International Settlements paper that came out a couple weeks ago - but they basically suggested that maybe R-star is - that R-star's time in the spotlight has kind of come and gone. And the idea is that, well, we should be focused more on what the actual inflation data is telling us, rather than some hypothetical unknown neutral rate that we're having to estimate and triangulate from a variety of factors. Does R-star still loom large in the Fed's thinking? Or do you think it's been sort of superseded by what we've seen in the real economy? </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-25" data-timestamp="12:47" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b> Well, I think we certainly spent a lot of time trying to understand and think about R-star and where it's headed. Not because I believe that it's - there's one precise point estimate. The standard deviations around most estimates are quite wide. </span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-26" data-timestamp="13:04" class="hawkish">But because I think you do have to ask yourself the question, "Are you restrictive or restrictive enough for what you're trying to do to inflation?" So you ask yourself that question. And if the economy comes in more robust, and inflation comes in more robust, then you ask yourself the question whether your prior assumption was right or not. And if it comes in south of where you thought, which is what happened for most of the 2010s, then you ask yourself the question of whether your estimate of R-star was too high. And so most estimates in the 2010s came down significantly.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="13:31" class="neutral">Some of that was done by models, some of that was done by just observation of an economy that didn't seem very robust despite extremely low rates. If our economy continues to be as robust it is with rates where they are, I think that'll tell you something. </span></p>
  
<p><b>Q: </b><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="13:45" class="neutral">If it's changed - why?</span></p> 
  
<p><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="13:48" class="neutral"><b>Tom Barkin: </b>There are a lot of people who are better at those models than I am. I think productivity would be a very simple way to explain the change a higher productivity economy is a higher trend growth economy, which would do it. You might argue fiscal has something to do with it and certainly we're at a different level of fiscal spend today than we were in the early 2010s. But again I'm not going to profess to be the expert on that.
  
<p><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="13:45" class="neutral">Q: Can I ask a question? Just, why is it 2%? Is it because of the expectations part is more important than the actual number? That's like, you're trying to set a something to aim for?</span></p> 

<p><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="14:20" class="neutral"><b>Tom barkin: </b>So, there was a debate, you know, "Why 2%?" There was a debate in the 90s, actually, and the Richmond Fed was right in the middle of it. Al brought us about what the right target should be.</span><span id="sentence-29" data-timestamp="14:28" class="neutral"> Interestingly, at the time, the choice was between 0% and 2%, right? Because our mandate is stable prices, and there were those who thought stable means stable. Stable - 0% is stable. It was widely debated, by the way, all the way till it was announced in 2012. But nowhere in that debate can you find evidence that people were debating 3%, 4%, or 5%. They were debating 1% or 1.5% or 2% or 0%. Why pick 2%? Well, a few things that are relevant. Pretty much every Central Bank in the world has 2%, plus or minus some have up to 2%, or 1.5% to 2.5%.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-30" data-timestamp="14:57" class="neutral"> Second is, it seems to have worked for 30 years. I mean, we actually delivered it, so it's not some random number you could never get to. Third, there is mismeasurement in there. And, and the mismeasurement is actually thought by most people to say that actual inflation is a little bit less than the 2% number. A good example would be encyclopedias. Um, uh, you used to buy - I used to buy encyclopedias. No one buys an encyclopedia today. It's on your phone. And so it's out of the index.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-31" data-timestamp="15:25" class="neutral">And so it's gone from being whatever World Book was - you know, $399 - to zero. That's deflation, but it's out of the index. And so technology - actually, you're not buying a camera anymore, or film - has taken a set of things out of the index that, you know, were deflationary. But maybe the best reason is, it's really hard to hit your target exactly. If you set a target at zero and you don't hit it exactly, you're in deflationary territory. And deflation is where everything tomorrow costs less than it does today.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-32" data-timestamp="15:53" class="neutral">So the incentive to buy today goes down, which means an economy, you know, tends to stagnate. And that's Japan and what it's been through. So two gives you a little bit of room against zero, means we can do a little bit to cut rates when we need to. That's the theory of it. And there's no - and you said, since it's worked, there's no need to change it at this point? Yeah, and in particular, you'd never change it before you hit it, right? And so we're out there trying to hit a target. </span></p> <p><span id="sentence-33" data-timestamp="16:20" class="hawkish">If inflation is at three and you decide, "Oh, new target's three," I just don't think that works for your credibility. And that's really the major tool the Fed has, is credibility.</span></p> 
  
  All right, Tom Barkin, thank you so much. That was fantastic. 
</span></p></span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Barkin" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chicago Fed President Goolsbee Sees Inflation Taking Longer to Return to 2%, Rates Remaining Restrictive</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/goolsbee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chicago Fed President Goolsbee Sees Inflation Taking Longer to Return to 2%, Rates Remaining Restrictive" /><published>2024-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/goolsbee</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/19/goolsbee.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}
</style>

<iframe src="https://players.brightcove.net/4934638106001/Sk7cO8ZDB_default/index.html?videoId=6351245284112" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0"></iframe>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-1" class="neutral">Joining us for the next session.</span> <span id="sentence-2" class="neutral">My name is Nick Timiraos, I cover the economy for the Wall Street Journal.</span> <span id="sentence-3" class="neutral">And I want to thank Sabu for having me to moderate this panel with Austin Goolsbee, who is the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago.</span> <span id="sentence-4" class="neutral">Austin previously served as the chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers for President Barack Obama, and was a professor at the University of Chicago.</span> <span id="sentence-5" class="neutral">So, Austin, let's get right into what we're seeing in the economy right now.</span> <span id="sentence-6" class="bold">But last week, there was an inflation report that showed that the CPI showed that now for three months, inflation has been a little bit firmer than maybe what people were expecting it after we had seen better readings at the end of last year.</span> <span id="sentence-7" class="neutral">My first question to you Austin is have the the first three readings this year on inflation changed your view about how long it's going to take to get inflation all the way back to the Feds 2% goal.</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-8" class="hawkish bold">Mechanically, yes. Just the way we add up the inflation. It's it's, it's going to make it it's going to take longer I always say one month is no months, but you know, three months that's that's at least one real month.</span> <span id="sentence-9" class="dovish">So if you take a broad view, inflation got way above where we were comfortable with and it's down a lot.</span> <span id="sentence-10" class="dovish">2023 was an excellent year for the mandate for the dual mandate that inflation fell as much close to as much as it's ever fallen.</span> <span id="sentence-11" class="neutral">And we did that without having an increase in unemployment, and without a recession, which is mostly unprecedented.</span> <span id="sentence-12" class="hawkish bold">But now that we're seeing after six, seven months of very strong improvement and close to 2% inflation, something that's well above that.</span> <span id="sentence-13" class="hawkish bold">Now, I think we have to recalibrate and we have we had to wait and see.</span> <span id="sentence-14" class="hawkish">I mean the it doesn't look like it's going to be as rapid as it looked for the previous six or seven months.</span> <span id="sentence-15" class="neutral">And I always say that I'm part of the you know, I'm one of the proud data dogs.</span> <span id="sentence-16" class="neutral">I looked up what's a gift, a group of dogs is either a pack or a kennel.</span> <span id="sentence-17" class="neutral">And so if you want to join the kennel of data dogs, the What's up first rule of the kennel if you are unclear stop walking and start sniffing and with these numbers we need to do more sniffing to to get the get where we are.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-18" class="neutral">Now the Fed is always looking ahead right you have to set policy based on the forecast for where you see the economy going did and so maybe, you know, a couple months ago, I don't know where your forecast was, but your colleagues, you know, put down projections and I think it was 2.4% core inflation at the end of this year that moved up a little bit.</span> <span id="sentence-19" class="neutral">In March 2.6%.</span> <span id="sentence-20" class="neutral">What difference does it really make?</span> <span id="sentence-21" class="neutral">If core inflation is at 2.4 or 2.7%?</span> <span id="sentence-22" class="neutral">At the end of this year, should that really make that big of a difference to how you're setting policy?</span> <span id="sentence-23" class="neutral">I mean, to be clear, inflation was 5% Almost 5% A year ago.</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-24" class="hawkish bold">He is look we're gonna get to 2% We said it that's the that's our stated target the mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-25" class="hawkish bold">We must in my view, we're credibility purposes and for content purposes, get inflation back to 2% if as the statement that the that the committee put out says we want to have confidence that we're on this path to to if you are confident that you're on a path to to the timing one month is no months you know, as I say if it's 2.4 in December, but it was 2.6 in November that that's not where it is.</span> <span id="sentence-26" class="neutral">It's but it's the broadly are we on path to 2% in a reasonable timeframe.</span> <span id="sentence-27" class="hawkish bold">And that's something that we got to they've got to pay attention to.</span> <span id="sentence-28" class="neutral">And I'm not it brings relief to my colleagues that I should have said at the outset.</span> <span id="sentence-29" class="neutral">I don't speak for anyone else on that committee.</span> <span id="sentence-30" class="neutral">I can only speak from my own opinion but in my opinion as a group, we're we don't just mechanically follow Hey, what was the CPI last month that should determine what the FOMC move should be next month?</span> <span id="sentence-31" class="neutral">I think that would be kind of a overlies that will be overly indexing on on one number.</span> <span id="sentence-32" class="neutral">Right.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-33" class="neutral">So the Fed has a dual mandate, price stability, which you've defined as 2.0% inflation over time, and then maximum employment, which I would interpret as a reasonably healthy labor market.</span> <span id="sentence-34" class="neutral">Last year, early this year you and you'd refer to this sort of soft landing as a golden path that we're on this golden path towards being able to achieve have the economy achieve those goals.</span> <span id="sentence-35" class="neutral">Without without a big trade off, right.</span> <span id="sentence-36" class="neutral">There has been a fear that maybe there will be a trade off.</span> <span id="sentence-37" class="neutral">Is that fair to say the golden path would would essentially be not much of a trade off but</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-38" class="neutral">yes, I was this was a reference to 2023 that if you take the history of not just the Fed but central banks in all the advanced economies, they virtually never got inflation down significantly without a deep recession.</span> <span id="sentence-39" class="neutral">So the trade off you're describing and I said through 2023 That because of supply chain healing, because labor force participation was rising, because productivity growth looked like it was relat stronger than trend and because fed credibility had not gone away.</span> <span id="sentence-40" class="neutral">So inflation expectations remained basically anchored at 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-41" class="dovish">That opened a door to the golden path that you could do, you could get inflation down without the trade off, and we did that so that happened in 2023.</span> <span id="sentence-42" class="dovish">That was a golden year.</span> <span id="sentence-43" class="hawkish bold">It's a It's definitely more difficult for 24 Because as the supply chain heals is not going to heal again.</span> <span id="sentence-44" class="hawkish">So the part that comes from that will be smaller.</span> <span id="sentence-45" class="dovish">I still think that the labor force participation and higher population growth because immigration that we didn't, some of those, make it a little Is it complicated?</span> <span id="sentence-46" class="neutral">It's not complicated, but they make you should just be a little hesitant to over interpret quantity numbers as an indicator of overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-47" class="neutral">Okay, so the center of the trade off, conflict comes if the economy starts overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-48" class="neutral">Then you got to decide do we want to do we which side of the mandate do we want to emphasize?</span> <span id="sentence-49" class="neutral">Right?</span> <span id="sentence-50" class="neutral">In a way it's been easy?</span> <span id="sentence-51" class="neutral">Not easy.</span> <span id="sentence-52" class="neutral">It's been straightforward, because we've been doing great on the employment side of the mandate unemployment rate 3.8%.</span> <span id="sentence-53" class="neutral">Many of us are old enough to remember 4% was supposed to be full employment.</span> <span id="sentence-54" class="neutral">So we've done great on the employment side and we have not succeeded over a multi year stint now, on the inflation side.</span> <span id="sentence-55" class="dovish">We did that in 23. without messing up the other side.</span> <span id="sentence-56" class="hawkish bold">My view of the level of monetary policy restrictiveness.</span> <span id="sentence-57" class="hawkish bold">If you just look at the real Fed funds rate, the interest rate minus inflation, that's high that's historically quite high as high as it's been in some decades.</span> <span id="sentence-58" class="hawkish bold">And and I would characterize you got to decide you will have to, if you hold that, at that level of restrictiveness for too long, you will definitely have to start thinking about the employment side of the mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-59" class="hawkish bold">To write and all of that hinges on inflation gotta keep coming down.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-60" class="hawkish bold">So I guess the question I'm building up to is have these first three months of the year where inflation looks like it's running closer to 3% than making more progress to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-61" class="neutral">The economy's adding jobs.</span> <span id="sentence-62" class="neutral">Maybe it's labor, supply driven immigration, so you don't have to worry about overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-63" class="neutral">But you also don't have to worry about you don't see obvious cracks in the labor market.</span> <span id="sentence-64" class="neutral">Has Has the data so far this year changed your view about whether you can hit your goals staying on this golden path, or are the trade offs going to become harder this year?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-65" class="hawkish bold">It definitely becomes harder this year.</span> <span id="sentence-66" class="neutral">And I've been saying that that 23 It was controversial when when I was saying in 23 that I thought we could get inflation down a lot without without a recession.</span> <span id="sentence-67" class="hawkish">As some of those factors we get the benefits of them.</span> <span id="sentence-68" class="hawkish bold">It definitely becomes more challenging and 24.</span> <span id="sentence-69" class="neutral">I sometimes find it helpful to break out the components of inflation, and kind of think through what happened so you started</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-70" class="neutral">doing this last year you said I started doing it last year, and goods came down and it stayed down and good</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-71" class="neutral">stayed down.</span> <span id="sentence-72" class="neutral">So the the the one topper sentence that I will say is we were at or below 2% COVID And that wasn't from AD the inflation rate of everything wasn't 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-73" class="neutral">Okay.</span> <span id="sentence-74" class="dovish">And it's important to remember that it doesn't have to be that housing inflation gets back to 2% and services back to 2% and goes back to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-75" class="neutral">It would that's not what it was before.</span> <span id="sentence-76" class="neutral">goods were at minus 1%.</span> <span id="sentence-77" class="neutral">services were at two and a half housing was three and a half.</span> <span id="sentence-78" class="neutral">That's what it was for the decade before COVID.</span> <span id="sentence-79" class="dovish">Goods are back to minus 1%.</span> <span id="sentence-80" class="dovish">deflation, largely from healing of the supply chain.</span> <span id="sentence-81" class="neutral">Services.</span> <span id="sentence-82" class="dovish">We're making progress they were above two and a half but they were coming down that services went way up for a couple of now for a couple of months.</span> <span id="sentence-83" class="hawkish bold">That's that's one we need to highlight and watch.</span> <span id="sentence-84" class="neutral">But this I consistently emphasize this housing part.</span> <span id="sentence-85" class="hawkish bold">That's the one that has not behaved the way we thought it would.</span> <span id="sentence-86" class="hawkish">So it's down from its peak, but it's still five and a half 6% inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-87" class="neutral">And mechanically we thought we understood how that number gets added up.</span> <span id="sentence-88" class="neutral">And the market rent inflation is well as well down.</span> <span id="sentence-89" class="neutral">But it hasn't flowed through into the official measures.</span> <span id="sentence-90" class="dovish">If it doesn't, I still think it will.</span> <span id="sentence-91" class="hawkish bold">But if it doesn't, I think we're going to have a hard time.</span> <span id="sentence-92" class="hawkish bold">It's definitely going to be more difficult to to get to 2% Overall, if we do not see progress on that.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-93" class="neutral">So let's take this hypothetical forward, then let's say that progress on housing continues but at a much slower rate than what you're expecting and maybe you have to wonder if housing is going to settle out at four, four and a half percent instead.</span> <span id="sentence-94" class="neutral">Of a free three and a half percent we have in the past decade.</span> <span id="sentence-95" class="neutral">In that situation.</span> <span id="sentence-96" class="neutral">Do you just accept inflation?</span> <span id="sentence-97" class="neutral">You know, let's say core PCE is running at two and three quarters.</span> <span id="sentence-98" class="neutral">Do you just accept that?</span> <span id="sentence-99" class="neutral">No.</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-100" class="hawkish bold">Well, look, we will get inflation back to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-101" class="hawkish">I don't know how to say it any different way we will get inflation back to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-102" class="hawkish bold">Now</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-103" class="neutral">I guess I'm not over what period of time when you over</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-104" class="hawkish bold">a reasonable period of time.</span> <span id="sentence-105" class="neutral">I'm not I'm not going to it's not over 20 years, but it's the answer to that is not a like is does that mean December of what year?</span> <span id="sentence-106" class="neutral">That's not how we think of it.</span> <span id="sentence-107" class="hawkish bold">It's on a are we on a reasonable path to get inflation down to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-108" class="dovish">And we had seven straight months at the end of last year where we were at 2% or even below.</span> <span id="sentence-109" class="neutral">So it is conceivable and there's not a it's not like breaking the speed of light that physicists tell you is impossible.</span> <span id="sentence-110" class="hawkish">But it's getting more complicated as we work through several of the beneficial things.</span> <span id="sentence-111" class="neutral">Of that we had in 23.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-112" class="hawkish bold">So let me ask you about the labor market that does job growth need to slow down for you to have more conviction that inflation is going to get to 2%</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-113" class="neutral">This, this gets at the is it the elephant in the room maybe it's the elephant and this gets at the elephant in the room is the inflation that we have seen in the last two months.</span> <span id="sentence-114" class="neutral">That followed on the disinflation that we saw for the second half of 23.</span> <span id="sentence-115" class="hawkish">Is this a sign of overheating?</span> <span id="sentence-116" class="neutral">Or is this something else?</span> <span id="sentence-117" class="neutral">We don't know the answer.</span> <span id="sentence-118" class="neutral">This is where the sniffing comes in.</span> <span id="sentence-119" class="neutral">Now we wait and we see and we we figure that out.</span> <span id="sentence-120" class="neutral">I just want us to be careful over indexing on jobs numbers looking strong when I gave this speech last year that that we talked about if you have positive supply developments happening like labor force participation rates going up like immigration bigger than what you thought so population is increasing, like productivity growth higher than trend.</span> <span id="sentence-121" class="neutral">Then you are going to get stronger quantity numbers aggregate GDP growth is going to be higher labor force, number of jobs created is going to be higher than what you thought was this steady state sustainable level.</span> <span id="sentence-122" class="neutral">And that's it so it's not you got to just be careful taking aggregate numbers as a sign of overheating in that environment.</span> <span id="sentence-123" class="neutral">So I'd say we're still looking, we still gotta understand what's the nature of economic growth and it's relevant in my eyes to look at what's happening in other countries, okay, so the growth experience in the United States, you've seen is well higher through and post COVID.</span> <span id="sentence-124" class="neutral">than in Europe and then in most other advanced economies.</span> <span id="sentence-125" class="neutral">If you start to see a rise in inflation all around the advanced economies, that's suggestive evidence that something else is happening like supply chain supply shocks, oil prices, etc.</span> <span id="sentence-126" class="neutral">And there are definitely geopolitical events and and the Taylor Swift album came out and other things that are that are influencing the whole world, not just the not just the United States, so I keep an eye on that too.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-127" class="neutral">So but back tying it back to this housing issue that you were on a minute ago.</span> <span id="sentence-128" class="neutral">I mean, rent is the main channel through which wages determine price why should we expect the kind of big housing disinflation that a lot of people have been looking for?</span> <span id="sentence-129" class="hawkish bold">If the labor market is holding up?</span> <span id="sentence-130" class="neutral">Okay,</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-131" class="neutral">we'd say so they say, so you said rent is what happens when wages meet housing,</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-132" class="neutral">that's kind of your I mean, I my job wages</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-133" class="neutral">are strong but if you think overheating, so So let's let's back up, there's two parts.</span> <span id="sentence-134" class="neutral">One is just specific to housing and the other is the overall what are the indicators of whether it's overheating or not overheating?</span> <span id="sentence-135" class="neutral">We got big jobs numbers.</span> <span id="sentence-136" class="neutral">We got very strong and stable consumer spending, and those are kind of the strongest parts of the economy.</span> <span id="sentence-137" class="neutral">There are other things in the job market that suggest you might call getting into better balance rather than spiraling up and overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-138" class="dovish">The vacancies the unemployment rate, coming back down closer to normal the voluntary quit rate back to little bull the basically matching what it was recovered wage growth moderating to something that depending what the productivity growth rate is, might be totally consistent with 2% inflation so that that doesn't feel exactly like overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-139" class="neutral">So that's why I say there's actually some cross currents, then on housing, as wage growth is moderating.</span> <span id="sentence-140" class="neutral">Is something like what it was pre COVID.</span> <span id="sentence-141" class="neutral">And as the market rents have come down to something like what they were pre COVID Or even below, that is what makes the puzzle of housing greater so the your, your puzzle, which is if wage growth is strong, then how could rents ever come down?</span> <span id="sentence-142" class="neutral">They did look at market rents, the market rents came down the puzzle right now is this mechanical puzzle of why is the official data looking so different from the from the market data, and I still we still don't know that, right?</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-143" class="neutral">So you've been clear that you need to see more, you need to be more confident that inflation is coming down to two before you cut rates.</span> <span id="sentence-144" class="hawkish">I want to ask about the other scenario under what circumstances would you say hey, you know what, we need to start thinking about raising interest rates maybe we haven't raised rates enough financial conditions haven't been tight enough maybe to provide meaning full support to reduce inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-145" class="neutral">How do you get into that?</span> <span id="sentence-146" class="neutral">You know, all scenario.</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-147" class="neutral">A never speculate.</span> <span id="sentence-148" class="neutral">That's how you don't as I always say, don't think that anything is never not on the table, you know, like the job of a central banker is the look, the job of central banker is to be paranoid about everything.</span> <span id="sentence-149" class="neutral">And and so we are about to contemplate all possible scenarios.</span> <span id="sentence-150" class="hawkish bold">We're going to get inflation back to 2%.</span> <span id="sentence-151" class="hawkish">I just didn't say that again.</span> <span id="sentence-152" class="hawkish">That's our thing.</span> <span id="sentence-153" class="hawkish bold">We will do that.</span> <span id="sentence-154" class="neutral">And now we're just trying to figure out how what is necessary.</span> <span id="sentence-155" class="neutral">how restrictive do we need to be and for any given level of rates, if you hold the rates where they are and you see inflation coming down?</span> <span id="sentence-156" class="hawkish">You are tightening, okay, because the real rate is getting bigger as inflation comes down.</span> <span id="sentence-157" class="dovish">If inflation is going up, you're loosening, even if you're holding it steady, and you know, this is the this is the toolkit we have this is a business we've chosen, you know, in the in the words of the Godfather, we have one tool and that tool is a screwdriver and we can tighten the thing and we can loosen a thing and that is the tool we have if your bumper fell off and tightening the screw was how to fix it.</span> <span id="sentence-158" class="neutral">That's great.</span> <span id="sentence-159" class="neutral">If it's like can you make me breakfast?</span> <span id="sentence-160" class="neutral">Where now?</span> <span id="sentence-161" class="neutral">Yeah, I said that before and somebody was like I have orange juice with vodka for breakfast.</span> <span id="sentence-162" class="neutral">I was like okay, then the tool will work but you know if it's, if it's not, if it's not in that then then we're you know, if it's hammer this thing together, then we we will need to think think that through, but I'm not going to I don't think it's productive to speculate on the should we raise what would be the condition hypothetically that you would raise rates that you would cut rates?</span> <span id="sentence-163" class="neutral">Because we have weeds months?</span> <span id="sentence-164" class="neutral">To find out we're going to get all this data my basic premise is the way you we should determine our monetary policy restrictiveness depends on what happens in the data.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-165" class="neutral">So is monetary policy tight right now?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-166" class="dovish bold">I think it's tight.</span> <span id="sentence-167" class="dovish bold">You know, I think like I said, I think take the real federal funds right there too.</span> <span id="sentence-168" class="neutral">There are two basic camps to answering that question.</span> <span id="sentence-169" class="neutral">There's three bay two and a half basic camps of how to answer that question.</span> <span id="sentence-170" class="neutral">One is to have a model and derive an R star and say is the are higher than the R star.</span> <span id="sentence-171" class="neutral">There is a historical comparison and then there is the de facto Pete I want to see pain and blood in the street.</span> <span id="sentence-172" class="neutral">And if I see that, then we're restrictive.</span> <span id="sentence-173" class="neutral">And if I don't see that, then we're not I'm more in the at this moment, that historical camp I just think the real federal funds rate is as high as has been in a long time.</span> <span id="sentence-174" class="dovish bold">If inflation keeps coming down, that is getting higher even as we're just sitting and waiting.</span> <span id="sentence-175" class="dovish bold">And if you hold at that level of restrictiveness for too long, then you got to start keeping your eye on the other side of the mandate to that you would start seeing slow down and all of those things I said of why don't over interpret strong quantity aggregate numbers, as overheating should be sobering in that environment.</span> <span id="sentence-176" class="neutral">If you let's say with added immigration and labor force participation that the true steady state job growth is 200,000 a month instead of 100,000 a month.</span> <span id="sentence-177" class="neutral">If you start seeing 100,000 or 80,000 you will you want to be a little careful of saying oh no, everything's fine, because actually that would be a sign that it's</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-178" class="neutral">that it's starting to go the other way.</span> <span id="sentence-179" class="neutral">So So I asked you about monetary policy and which is you're trying to type policies trying to reduce aggregate demand, right?</span> <span id="sentence-180" class="neutral">What about the stance of macro?</span> <span id="sentence-181" class="neutral">Economic Policy more broadly, we have the IRA and the chips Act, which are proven to be more popular, you see some more subsidies going out?</span> <span id="sentence-182" class="neutral">Or you may have a multiplier effect or TSMC or Intel says we're going to invest here alongside the US.</span> <span id="sentence-183" class="neutral">Is it possible that macro economic policy, even though monetary policy is tight that fiscal policy is to some extent offsetting what you at the Fed are doing?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-184" class="neutral">I joined the Fed.</span> <span id="sentence-185" class="neutral">If you become a Fed woman or a Fed man, you get out of the fiscal policy business so I'm not as the Chicago fed.</span> <span id="sentence-186" class="neutral">I always say I look our motto is a Midwest thing.</span> <span id="sentence-187" class="neutral">There is no bad weather there is only bad clothing, you give us that conditions and we'll deal with it and and if the fifth to me the fiscal policy input that just the conditions we'll look we'll figure out I don't know is the answer.</span> <span id="sentence-188" class="neutral">I could conceive of a scenario let's say we saw in the 2000s, China booming, booming, booming like crazy driving up the price of a whole series of commodities, and that was having a tough impact.</span> <span id="sentence-189" class="neutral">On a lot of other countries because they are dealing with the with those costs.</span> <span id="sentence-190" class="neutral">There are definitely things that can happen that change the underlying conditions that have nothing to do with monetary policy for sure.</span> <span id="sentence-191" class="neutral">That's true.</span> <span id="sentence-192" class="neutral">The second part of the question relates to a broader thing, which is sort of what can the Feds how much impact does the Fed's monetary policy have on business investment on traditional drivers and one of the complications of this moment this these last two, three years moment is that the traditional business cycle I told you, we have one tool basically we can tighten we can loosen and that normally works because the business cycle the most cyclically sensitive industries are also the most interest rate sensitive industries.</span> <span id="sentence-193" class="neutral">And so, it usually monetary policy is the direct stabilizer.</span> <span id="sentence-194" class="neutral">And what happened this time as you know, is that we had a recession that was driven by nobody can go to the dentist and consumer durables demand went way up in the recession.</span> <span id="sentence-195" class="neutral">And so now if you ask the question, how interest rate sensitive are elective plastic surgeries?</span> <span id="sentence-196" class="neutral">I have no idea and you know what we're so we're we were trying to match our tool to the moment and and that's not totally straightforward,</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-197" class="neutral">but we have I mean, we have 6% Close to 6% deficits and a peacetime full employment full employment economy, which we haven't seen.</span> <span id="sentence-198" class="neutral">Is that making it harder to get inflation back down?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-199" class="neutral">Look, like I say whatever the condition, you see what the inflation rate is, you see what the GDP growth rate is we can see employment.</span> <span id="sentence-200" class="neutral">If you're alleging that's from fiscal policy in the United States, some people are alleging it's because slowdowns elsewhere in the world what the value of the dollar whatever there you can have anything in your model.</span> <span id="sentence-201" class="neutral">But at the end of the day, the Fed people have to take the conditions and make forecasts of the conditions and respond to those and that's what we're gonna do.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-205" class="neutral">So you were talking a little bit earlier, has your estimate for the neutral rate of interest.</span> <span id="sentence-206" class="neutral">This is sort of the Nirvana where you're at your goal, you're probably you know, there's no shocks in the economy, very rare, but you know, you have to have some kind of estimate of what your neutral rate might be in that scenario.</span> <span id="sentence-207" class="neutral">Has your neutral rate estimate gone up?</span> <span id="sentence-208" class="neutral">Do you think there's a short run neutral rate that might be you know, higher right now but comes down to policy gets more restrictive is that they</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-209" class="neutral">pulled a sleight of hand they're okay to call it the neutral rate is better.</span> <span id="sentence-210" class="neutral">Our star I budgeted hours and that's the same thing.</span> <span id="sentence-211" class="neutral">But when you say it as our star, then you realize like, wait a minute, somebody's got like a mathematical formula in there.</span> <span id="sentence-212" class="neutral">And to call it neutral is to make it sound better than my thing about our star and you can ask the research staff they don't like that.</span> <span id="sentence-213" class="neutral">I said, I started calling it our Sasquatch, because it's not fundamentally not observable.</span> <span id="sentence-214" class="neutral">Okay.</span> <span id="sentence-215" class="neutral">And so you can have their two styles of how do you identify what is our star?</span> <span id="sentence-216" class="neutral">One is you can build a model and John Williams as as done some of the most pathbreaking work on building those models and what goes into the model there are a bunch of slow moving things like demographics and and stuff like that.</span> <span id="sentence-217" class="neutral">Or you can indirectly say well, this was the policy and inflation was still rising.</span> <span id="sentence-218" class="neutral">So it must be that our star was higher.</span> <span id="sentence-219" class="neutral">I'm a little impatient with the r star is a long run concept and our whole debate in public seems to be about a short run long run rate.</span> <span id="sentence-220" class="neutral">And that's, I'm uncomfortable with that even concept, which really leads me back to the I'm mostly looking at the historical, recent historical, what's the real federal funds rate?</span> <span id="sentence-221" class="neutral">That's kind of my indicator.</span> <span id="sentence-222" class="neutral">Now, if you really want an R star, you can back out from the median SAP, they ask what do you think that rate will be in the long run?</span> <span id="sentence-223" class="neutral">And I think that median SCP is like two and a half percent.</span> <span id="sentence-224" class="neutral">And that might have moved a little bit but it hadn't moved a ton.</span> <span id="sentence-225" class="neutral">And you don't think of things like ours are moving a ton in the short run.</span> <span id="sentence-226" class="neutral">So I, I guess I'm a little impatient with the argument that you would see wild swings in long run interest rates over a short run period.</span></p>
<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-227" class="neutral">I want to turn it over to questions from the audience.</span> <span id="sentence-228" class="neutral">Are there any, any questions in the audience?</span> <span id="sentence-229" class="neutral">We have a mic if you could state your name and affiliation.</span></p>
<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-230" class="neutral">James Madore.</span> <span id="sentence-231" class="neutral">I work for Newsday, and I want to ask you a little bit about the impact of migration, immigration, on our economy, because obviously we are seeing more people come to the country, the state that I live in lives and dies on immigration.</span> <span id="sentence-232" class="neutral">So how is immigration going to affect our economy in the short term and the long term?</span> <span id="sentence-233" class="neutral">Okay, super deep question.</span> <span id="sentence-234" class="neutral">Which I'm mostly not going to answer but I'm gonna say for us for fed where we are thing is dual mandate law tells us fed your job is stabilize prices, maximize employment.</span> <span id="sentence-235" class="dovish">How does immigration affect stabilizing prices and maximizing of employment A, it means aggregate job growth is higher than otherwise because population is growing in a way the measures of overheating in the economy are kind of per capita.</span> <span id="sentence-236" class="dovish">And so if the Capita is getting bigger, the aggregate total can be bigger on inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-237" class="neutral">I don't know what the impact on wages are at various parts of the distribution.</span> <span id="sentence-238" class="neutral">But I do know that there are some sectors in the economy that have had massive labor shortages through the COVID times where there are a high share of the workforce or immigrants and leisure and hospitality and in some of the other categories, you would think that you would see job growth stronger in those.</span> <span id="sentence-239" class="dovish">So I think in the short run, that there is more immigration makes the dual mandate goals a little easier to accomplish.</span> <span id="sentence-240" class="neutral">And then there's always the caveat of but isn't everything relative to what you expected it was going to be.</span> <span id="sentence-241" class="neutral">And there I don't so one thing we found out the CBO put out this report on immigration and it said last year, there were millions more people than we thought there were that it feels very impactful.</span> <span id="sentence-242" class="neutral">If everybody knows how many people are going to come in and then as many people exactly as many people as what we thought are what come in.</span> <span id="sentence-243" class="neutral">I think there are some aspects in which that's less impactful.</span>

<p><b>Lillian Berbick:</b><span id="sentence-1" class="neutral">Lillian Berbick Oregon Public Broadcasting.</span> <span id="sentence-2" class="neutral">I have a nerdy question and no fun question.</span> <span id="sentence-3" class="neutral">Are those different?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-4" class="neutral">They might be the same in this audience.</span> <span id="sentence-5" class="neutral">So my nerdy question is, you mentioned that you have kind of one tool in the toolbox.</span> <span id="sentence-6" class="neutral">But there's actually another tool that the Fed has that we haven't really seen be used, which is reserve requirements.</span> <span id="sentence-7" class="neutral">Do you feel like especially with some of the smaller bank failures that we saw last year of changing reserve requirements?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-8" class="neutral">This opens the door lens in the whole discussion about both the balance sheet and the what the capital requirements are.</span> <span id="sentence-9" class="neutral">I'm not going to get into the regulatory the banking system I view is overall, the safety and soundness of the banking system.</span> <span id="sentence-10" class="hawkish bold">Hinges critically on have them having adequate capital, I believe that they do have that but Vice Chair bar is is kind of the point person thinking through those.</span> <span id="sentence-11" class="neutral bold">The balance sheet is another tool in a way in the spirit of reserve requirements, but remember, brought broadly defined is still the same tool.</span> <span id="sentence-12" class="neutral bold">We're operating through a channel of through a credit channel that can be tightening or loosening.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-13" class="neutral">I'm a little uneasy if we draw we're trying to get sector specific in our like there's no monetary policy that's just for the housing industry just for manufacturing or or that kind of thing.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-14" class="neutral">I think mostly what we do on Capitol for banks should be about safety and soundness of the banking system.</span> <span id="sentence-15" class="neutral bold">Not really monetary policy and on the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-16" class="neutral bold">We've been doing this Qt and running down the balance sheet, but everybody should understand that under the way we do monetary policy now since 2006, or seven or whenever we change to the so called ample reserves regime.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-17" class="neutral bold">You've got to have enough balance sheet that the private sector is not out, trying to hoard its own liquidity.</span> <span id="sentence-18" class="neutral bold">And that means the balance sheet is going to be bigger on a steady state basis than it ever was in the old days.</span> <span id="sentence-19" class="neutral bold">And if you get it too small.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-20" class="neutral">As I kind of say, my understanding is that the human body can live for three to four days with no water before you die.</span> <span id="sentence-21" class="neutral">And how long exactly depends on conditions?</span> <span id="sentence-22" class="neutral">Is it hot?</span> <span id="sentence-23" class="neutral">How human is it?</span> <span id="sentence-24" class="neutral">You know, did you drink a Gatorade right before you started?</span> <span id="sentence-25" class="neutral">But do you want to know like, what do we really want to figure out?</span> <span id="sentence-26" class="neutral">Oh no, it's 37 hours or it's played out like how many hours we're going to get to a point where the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-27" class="neutral bold">It's definitely not a fixed number.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-28" class="neutral bold">It's probably not even a constant share of GDP, but it's going to be close to a constant share of GDP and GDP grows.</span> <span id="sentence-29" class="neutral bold">So balance sheet will stop shrinking will start growing eventually.</span> <span id="sentence-30" class="neutral">And it is kind of related to this question of bank reserves.</span> <span id="sentence-31" class="neutral bold">I don't think of that.</span> <span id="sentence-32" class="neutral bold">I think of that as something separate from our what we're doing with monetary policy.</span> <span id="sentence-33" class="neutral">Okay, time for the fun question.</span> <span id="sentence-34" class="neutral">Yeah, that well I thought that was a fun.</span> <span id="sentence-35" class="neutral">What's the I agree?</span></p>

<p>Lillian Berbick: <span id="sentence-36" class="neutral">Um, so, you know, reporting on monetary policy and fed movements can get really rote.</span> <span id="sentence-37" class="neutral">Like, here, we're gonna get to 2% is about a week and I say how was that wrote?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-38" class="neutral">Is there any stories about monetary policy and economic data that you wish were being told by journalists?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-39" class="neutral">let's answer a different question.</span> <span id="sentence-41" class="neutral">But related, the what?</span> <span id="sentence-42" class="neutral">What have we been missing?</span> <span id="sentence-43" class="dovish bold">If productivity growth is going to be as fast as it's been for the last three quarters?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-44" class="dovish bold">That's fundamentally going to change everything about the economy in a way and it would have direct implications for monetary policy.</span> <span id="sentence-45" class="dovish bold">It would put us back in an environment that would very much be like the late 90s, where you can have faster wage growth, without inflation gonna have faster GDP growth without generating inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-46" class="neutral">And that's a series that is noisy but it's worth absolutely paying attention to that.</span> <span id="sentence-47" class="neutral">That's not even mostly about the Fed.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-48" class="neutral bold">But it has definite implications for the Fed.</span> <span id="sentence-49" class="neutral">So I will watch that.</span> <span id="sentence-50" class="neutral">If you ask, are there stories about the Fed?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-51" class="neutral">Yes.</span> <span id="sentence-52" class="neutral">And I've dried so one of the stories was in Detroit, Chicago Fed has a Detroit branch.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-53" class="neutral">And our Detroit employees are super loyal to the Detroit Lions.</span> <span id="sentence-54" class="neutral">And the Detroit Lions after decades of being horrible, almost made the Superbowl and we run hundreds of millions of dollars of cash in and out of the Feds each day because we're we're bank to the banks.</span> <span id="sentence-55" class="neutral">So when they put cash in their ATMs, it's coming from us.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-56" class="neutral">So we have these bomb dogs, and our bomb dogs moonlight as the bomb sniffing dogs at the lions game.</span> <span id="sentence-57" class="neutral">So I told the people I was like, these are the hardest working dogs in Detroit.</span> <span id="sentence-58" class="neutral">You got to get them because some press coverage and they did.</span> <span id="sentence-59" class="neutral">They got up they went they went on TV and there were the dogs and N eyes.</span> <span id="sentence-60" class="neutral">I had said nothing to their greatest sniffing they're in the data dog kennel like I asked for permission.</span> <span id="sentence-61" class="neutral">Can I join you?</span> <span id="sentence-62" class="neutral">You know it was effing out the bonds.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-63" class="neutral">I said that if the lions one I was gonna give each of these dogs there's two of them over there Fox and.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-64" class="neutral">And krill Fox and krill I said Fox and krill get a steak.</span> <span id="sentence-65" class="neutral">We're gonna get a steak and give it to each one.</span> <span id="sentence-66" class="neutral">The Lions laws but then they had a vote of the Fed employees and by a 95 to five vote.</span> <span id="sentence-67" class="neutral">They said it wasn't the dog's fault that they went forward on fourth down.</span> <span id="sentence-68" class="neutral">So we gave him the stakes anyway.</span> <span id="sentence-69" class="neutral">And so there is a human side to the feds, especially the regional Feds that that is worth that is worth covering their role in the in the community right down here.</span> 
  <p><b>Sarah Foster: </b><span id="sentence-70" class="neutral">It would probably be wrong to call this a fun question, but thank you for being here, letting us ask you this.</span> <span id="sentence-71" class="neutral">I'm Sarah Foster at Bankrate.</span> <span id="sentence-72" class="neutral">I'm curious what you think about delinquency rates right now, particularly for credit cards and auto loans.</span> <span id="sentence-73" class="neutral">They've been rising even though the unemployment rate is low.</span> <span id="sentence-74" class="neutral">What would happen if there is a slight increase in the unemployment rate and kind of two part question?</span> <span id="sentence-75" class="neutral">Yeah, you know, considering how much more debt consumers have how some auto loans off cars are obviously not worth what they were a few years ago.</span> <span id="sentence-76" class="neutral">Could a slight increase results and maybe something slightly more painful thing worse?</span></p>
  
  <p>Austan Goolsbee: </p><span id="sentence-77" class="neutral">Okay.</span> <span id="sentence-78" class="neutral">This is this an important question.</span> <span id="sentence-79" class="neutral">I'm glad you raised it when I talked about the crosscurrents.</span> <span id="sentence-80" class="neutral">And I said, Look, there's some things about the job market that don't really look like overheating.</span> <span id="sentence-81" class="neutral">They look like coming back to normal.</span> <span id="sentence-82" class="hawkish">There are also some measures in the economy that historically do not portend well.</span> <span id="sentence-83" class="hawkish">So, if you look at normal times, if the delinquencies rate of consumer loans starts rising, that is often a leading indicator for things are about to get worse.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-84" class="neutral">The only thing so that that is an area of concern.</span> <span id="sentence-85" class="neutral">What people are trying to figure out right now is that's went way down.</span> <span id="sentence-86" class="neutral">Okay, so it is rising, but the level that it's risen to is if I just told you the level and you compare that to pre COVID It doesn't look that different, but if I told you delinquencies went up by however many percent you would say, Oh, if they go up that much, that's a terrible sign.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-87" class="neutral">So that's a different way to say we don't know sniffing Musk commands.</span> <span id="sentence-88" class="neutral">You know where that's one we're watching the consumer balance sheet got unprecedentedly strong after stimulus that the excess savings you're you're familiar with that that old fight so I think much of that is gone.</span> <span id="sentence-89" class="dovish">We're back to more normal levels.</span> <span id="sentence-90" class="dovish bold">Overall consumer debt levels are not especially high.</span> <span id="sentence-91" class="hawkish bold">But look, as you know, when things start to turn wrong on the real side of the economy, that doesn't just tend to be like, Oh, that happened one month and then they don't continue.</span> <span id="sentence-92" class="hawkish bold">So that's that's our concern.</span> <span id="sentence-93" class="hawkish bold">I think this consumer delinquencies is one of the that's one of the more concerning parts in the in the data at this moment.</span> </p>

<p><b>Chuck Jaffe: </b><span id="sentence-96" class="neutral">Chuck Jaffe, with money life and the Fed historically, and what experts say all the time is that the Fed doesn't necessarily make moves until things break.</span> <span id="sentence-97" class="neutral">But a lot of the time Well, a lot of people who were watching and expecting rate cuts this year, were saying that if the Fed made them early this year, that the Fed was moving from a position of strength, but now that rate cuts and I know you're not going to speculate on what's going to cause them or when they're going to happen.</span> <span id="sentence-98" class="neutral">But now that we are looking at rate cuts taking longer when the Fed finally moves on rate cuts, will it be moving from a position of strength or will it be moving from a position of weakness?</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-99" class="neutral">The only reason I hesitate is that last part of is that a position of strength or position of weakness on the ground I can't I can't fully understand what what that means.</span> <span id="sentence-100" class="neutral">Like what like what does it mean to be a position of weakness or position you are forced to act because otherwise you will get to that or things break.</span> <span id="sentence-101" class="neutral">If you don't do that you're gonna fall behind they're gonna fall behind.</span> <span id="sentence-102" class="hawkish">Okay, if we don't want to always be late.</span> <span id="sentence-103" class="hawkish">We want to anticipate and that's the language in the statement of are we on a path to 2% inflation connotes that to my mind that we are forward looking we're not you don't just want to have what happened last month to the CPI that should determine what the rate should be.</span> <span id="sentence-104" class="neutral">Now, that said when the SEP comes out, so like, take in December, the Feds median, SEP said there would be three rate cuts and 24 and the market immediately concluded that must mean seven.</span> <span id="sentence-105" class="neutral">And they and so then the market said they're going to be seven cuts.</span> <span id="sentence-106" class="neutral">And then Nick is how to be so why do you say three if the market says seven?</span> <span id="sentence-107" class="neutral">Look, the thing is, there's only eight meetings a year.</span> <span id="sentence-108" class="neutral">So my thing is you faff around you're gonna find out you know, and so the Silicon Valley just click up don't don't fight the Fed.</span> <span id="sentence-109" class="neutral">We had a board member was said he tells us people, we can fight the Fed as long as we want but the last time I checked, they're still undefeated.</span> <span id="sentence-110" class="neutral">And there is a component of Silicon Valley Bank had hedges on the interest rate and they got rid of the hedges.</span> <span id="sentence-111" class="neutral">If you go back and read the bar report.</span> <span id="sentence-112" class="neutral">Why did they get rid of the hedges?</span> <span id="sentence-113" class="neutral">Because they took a bet.</span> <span id="sentence-114" class="neutral">The Fed will never raise rates as much as they as they say, and the market is telling us that the rates are going to come down.</span><span id="sentence-116" class="neutral">I'm not.</span> <span id="sentence-117" class="neutral">I came from the old school.</span> <span id="sentence-118" class="neutral">My friend and mentor was Paul Volcker.</span> <span id="sentence-119" class="neutral">And Paul Volcker used to always say our job is to act and their job is to react and let's not get the order mixed up.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-120" class="hawkish">So I think that means I'm saying whether we wait or don't wait, we're always operating from a position of strength.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-121" class="hawkish">And we should be forward looking definitely not just backward looking.</span></p>

<p><b>Nick Timiraos:</b> <span id="sentence-122" class="neutral">Before before we finish, I want to be stuck.</span> <span id="sentence-123" class="neutral">But in we only have time for one but actually yet another one.</span> <span id="sentence-124" class="neutral">So we didn't talk about the election.</span> <span id="sentence-125" class="neutral">I thought it might come up in the q&amp;a.</span> <span id="sentence-126" class="neutral">You know, before you took this job.</span> <span id="sentence-127" class="neutral">You spent time in the political arena, you would go on Fox News as you know, defend the Democratic Party priorities.</span> <span id="sentence-128" class="neutral">You were very critical of Donald Trump, especially after he lost the election.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-129" class="neutral">And I know the Fed says it doesn't take politics into account but given how you felt about Trump.</span> <span id="sentence-130" class="neutral">Can you unseal that when you're balancing the trade offs?</span> <span id="sentence-131" class="neutral">Look, I told you I'm a Fed man.</span> <span id="sentence-132" class="neutral">Now and the Fed does not include elections in our we have a mandate there's nothing about even if you elections in the mandate, there's nothing about the stock market.</span></p>

<p><b>Austan Goolsbee:</b> <span id="sentence-133" class="neutral">Are you tell me the weather I tell you what code I'm wearing with this what we're doing I have no, you you read this minutes.</span> <span id="sentence-134" class="neutral">You read the transcripts?</span> <span id="sentence-135" class="neutral">The FOMC The elections are not in the transcripts, and they shouldn't be the mandate is what the dual mandate is what drives our decisions.</span> <span id="sentence-136" class="neutral">And that's what's going to drive our decisions this year.</span> <span id="sentence-137" class="neutral">Austin, thank you for joining us.</span> <span id="sentence-138" class="neutral">Stay tuned.</span>
</p></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Goolsbee" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fed’s Kashkari Stresses Inflation Stall-Out Necessitates Patience on Rate Cuts</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/kashkari.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fed’s Kashkari Stresses Inflation Stall-Out Necessitates Patience on Rate Cuts" /><published>2024-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/kashkari</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/kashkari.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://video.foxnews.com/v/embed.js?id=6351187887112&amp;w=466&amp;h=263"></script>
<noscript>Watch the latest video at <a href="https://www.foxnews.com">foxnews.com</a></noscript>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Are you surprised that mortgage rates would be following that the 30 year fixed rate now up to seven point 10% Heights, it's been more than four months what to make of that and these growing expectations that rate cuts that the markets were planning on might be getting pushed back further and further and further gentlemen, who would know is Neel Kashkari. He's the Minneapolis Federal Reserve Bank president. Neil, very good to have you.</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> Good to see you, Neil.</p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Um, let me ask you first about what's happening on the mortgage front. You know, I know that that seems like a jarring number to some. I don't know if I ever told you what my wife and I paid for our first mortgage, but I've told the nation I think about 2000 times, but it was a lot higher. And I know it's what you get used to and people now we're getting used to much lower rates and it's putting a stall some say a stop to the housing industry. Do you agree with that?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">I don't agree with that.</span> <span class="neutral">One of the surprises for me, is how resilient housing the housing market broadly, has been in the last couple of years while we've raised interest rates, as you noted, you know, mortgage rates are now above 7%.</span> <span class="hawkish">I would have thought that that would have slammed the brakes on the housing market.</span> <span class="neutral">What we've seen is the single family home market has slowed down.</span> <span class="neutral">The multifamily market or apartment building market is kept up much stronger.</span> <span class="neutral">And if you look at construction, employment, construction, employment has continued to climb throughout this period when we've been raising interest rates.</span> <span class="neutral">So actually, it's a little bit of a head scratcher for me.</span> <span class="neutral">How is it that housing has been as resilient as it has been?</span> <span class="neutral">And I think part of the answer is, for the 10 years or so after the financial crisis.</span> <span class="neutral">We simply didn't build enough units, homes or apartment buildings to keep up with our population growth.</span> <span class="neutral">And that demand is still built up there that we're trying to work its way through Yeah, that there's limited supply and the demand for that.</span> <span class="neutral">Having said that, there's not more supply likely to come on the market right now.</span> <span class="neutral">If you're a home seller and you're looking at this environment, you're going to hold off right and that limits choices for potential buyers.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> So how do you see that Mexican standoff going?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">Well, you know, every person we hear this a lot that well, people aren't selling their homes, because they're they've locked in a low mortgage rate and they don't want to buy a new home and have to go get a more expensive mortgage and that that makes a lot of sense.</span> <span class="neutral">But that also means that's one fewer buyer in the market.</span> <span class="neutral">So how that washes out is a little bit unclear to me.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">Ultimately, we know what we need to do, we need to get inflation back down to 2%.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Once we do that, we get closer to it.</span> <span class="dovish">We'd be in a position to start dialing back some of our interest rate increases, and then you would expect that to flow through to cheaper mortgages for American families.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Let me ask you a little bit about this given some of the inflation numbers we had seen and the robust economic numbers we've seen in other areas. market rates have been backing up over which the Fed has no direct control, it can Jawbone about them one way or the other, but no direct control. And I am wondering now whether this is pushed off those expected rate cuts to either late next year or maybe not at all this year?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral bold">Well, you know, the data is going to guide us we've been surprised in a concerning way about the first three months inflation data this year, the second half of last year, we saw a lot of progress as inflation fell back towards our target.</span> <span class="dovish">That gave us a lot of optimism that maybe 2% inflation or for is around the corner.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">And now things seem to have stalled out.</span> <span class="hawkish">So my view is we just need to sit here and be patient until we see the data and hopefully get convinced that inflation continues to fall back down.</span> <span class="neutral bold">The good news is as you indicated, the economy continues to be strong.</span> <span class="neutral bold">GDP growth is strong.</span> <span class="neutral bold">Consumer spending is strong and the labor market is strong.</span> <span class="neutral">So we're in a good position from which to take our time before we decide where to go with interest rates.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Take your time until next year.</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">Well, I mean, potentially I dialed in in March I had dialed in to interest rate cuts this year to 25 basis point cuts.</span> <span class="neutral">That was before some of the data that we've seen.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">I'm in the I'm in the view of we need to wait and see be patient as long as it takes until we get convinced that inflation is on its way back down to 2%.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> So to be clear, you would have been factoring in on that. So we'll dotplot we're all you guys get together and compare where you see rates going or what you would ideally like to see the two rate cuts. Are you down to one right now or are you down to done?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">You know, we don't have to make that decision until June.</span> <span class="neutral">So I'm going to hold off making that decision but certainly the data that we've seen a year right now.</span> <span class="neutral">I was permitted during commercial No.</span> <span class="neutral">We need to see the labor market data and the inflation data as well as spending</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> how much does all of this spending in Washington complicate things because that is in itself inflationary not exclusively, but it doesn't help your your cause does it?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">It complicates things you know what we know that a lot of stimulus was part of the driver not the only driver but a contributor to the high inflation that we've seen.</span> <span class="neutral">If you when I go out and I look at Where's investment taking place, where construction taking place we know for example, the spending on infrastructure, the spending on new chip plans, all of that on the margin is inflationary.</span> <span class="neutral">Is it big enough to move inflation at the national economy level?</span> <span class="neutral">That's a little bit unclear.</span> <span class="neutral">But we are a little bit at cross purposes where you have some programs that that are really well meaning and for good reason that Congress is focused on at the meantime, we're trying to get demand down in the economy.</span> <span class="neutral">So there are some complications that we're having to navigate right now.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> I know you don't like to wade into politics deal and everyone likes to say the Federal Reserve is above politics, but it has moved in election. years in the past presidential election years. It's not, you know, immune to doing so. But we do know that President Trump had a very, you know, change a big change in how he thought of Jerome Powell and doesn't think much of him now, probably if he became President wouldn't have reappointed to head the Federal Reserve. So how much does this environment weigh on you guys?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="hawkish">You know, in some sense, it makes things easy, because the higher the political heat gets turned up from either party, the more we all know, we just need to focus on our goals that Congress has given us Congress told us go achieve maximum employment and stable prices that we define as inflation, we call it our dual mandate.</span> <span class="neutral">And the higher the temperature get, the more we all just hug the data and hug the dual mandate.</span> <span class="neutral">That's the only way we can figure it out.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> People have that data through the prism of their own political point of view, not all the time. But sometimes, right? There are a lot of people who are supporting Donald Trump who say that any cutting interest rates right now would be unwise, and would only be meant to help Joe Biden, how do you answer that?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">Well, I would just suggest to those folks that look at the data that we talk about, we talk about what data we're focused on all the time.</span> <span class="neutral">We talk about what data we're looking at, and look at the data.</span> <span class="neutral">Is it matching what we're saying that's motivating our actions or inactions?</span> <span class="neutral">Ultimately I think that that's going to be the proof.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Are we walking the walk that we laid out to you when you see some of the names that have been raised? Or hinted at to be the next Fed chairman? They're outsiders and people who are not presently serving on the Federal Reserve right now. And I just learned it but with art laffer being among them and a host of other former Trump administration officials do you do you get concerned about that? Do you ever say, jeez, where am I on this list?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">You know, that's not my job to consider who's gonna get appointed or whatnot.</span> <span class="neutral">I'll say, you know, the any appointee from any president ultimately has to get confirmed by the United States Senate.</span> <span class="neutral">And I think senators on both sides of the aisle have said the Fed picks are really important and that they give them careful scrutiny and consideration.</span> <span class="neutral">And so I've actually got a lot of confidence in our process, that good people will continue to get appointed to the Fed, regardless of who's president.</span> <span class="neutral">We have two term limits on presidents.</span> <span class="neutral">It seems limitless for Fed Chairman</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> Do you think two and done is good enough?</p>

<p><b>Neel Kashkari:</b> <span class="neutral">You know, I think Alan Greenspan served for more than two terms, and I think did a very good job during his term.</span> <span class="neutral">You know, Ben Bernanke served two terms.</span> <span class="neutral">I think that'll be up to the president to make the right call.</span></p>

<p><b>Neil:</b> That's a very, very, you know, threading the needle answer that was that was well played, Neil. Very good, saying. Thank you very much.</p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Kashkari" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NY Fed’s Williams Suggests Higher Rates for Longer as Strong Economy Outweighs Inflation Concerns</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/williams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NY Fed’s Williams Suggests Higher Rates for Longer as Strong Economy Outweighs Inflation Concerns" /><published>2024-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/williams</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/18/williams.html"><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.</p>

<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<div id="youtube-player-container"></div>

<!-- Load the IFrame Player API code asynchronously -->
<script src="https://www.youtube.com/iframe_api"></script>

<script>
  var player;
  function onYouTubeIframeAPIReady() {
    player = new YT.Player('youtube-player-container', {
      height: '315',
      width: '560',
      videoId: 'HcqP4JvE2MU'
    });
  };

function seekToTime(timestamp) {
  var timeArr = timestamp.split(":");
  var hours = 0;
  var minutes = 0;
  var seconds = 0;

  // Check if the timestamp includes hours
  if (timeArr.length === 3) {
    hours = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[2], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 2) {
    // If the timestamp is only minutes and seconds
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 1) {
    // If the timestamp is only seconds
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
  }

  // Calculate total seconds
  var totalSeconds = hours * 3600 + minutes * 60 + seconds;

  // Seek to the specified time if possible
  if (player && player.seekTo) {
    player.seekTo(totalSeconds, true);
  }
}


// Attach click event listeners to each sentence
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function() {
  document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(span) {
    span.addEventListener("click", function() {
      // Remove highlighting/underscore from all spans
      document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(otherSpan) {
        otherSpan.classList.remove("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      });
      
      // Add highlighting/underscore to the clicked span
      this.classList.add("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      
      // Seek the video to the timestamp
      var timestamp = this.getAttribute("data-timestamp");
      seekToTime(timestamp);
    });
  });
});

</script>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> Please welcome John Williams, President and CEO of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York. Good morning everyone. I did not know that David was so funny. We'll see if John can bring the jokes. No pressure. Obviously, we're here when a lot of Central Bank Governors and Finance ministers are in town, and the Fed is the talk of the town. You have an important role as a permanent member of the Fed rate-setting committee. We just heard J. Powell throw some cold water on the idea that the Fed could possibly cut rates later this year, as it had projected earlier. Are we in a "higher for longer" stage where we could see this pushed off to next year?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-1" data-timestamp="24:24" class="neutral">Well, first of all, we always say that we're data-dependent, and the data have been really pretty good on the economy. We added 3 million jobs last year. Job growth still has been very strong coming into the first quarter of this year. </span> <span id="sentence-2" data-timestamp="24:56" class="hawkish bold">GDP growth's been strong. All signs of consumer spending are strong. So we have a strong economy, we want a strong economy, that's all very good news. But it also means that the high rates that we have haven't caused the economy to slow too much. It seems like monetary policy is working the way we hoped it would. We're seeing imbalances in the economy come down. We're seeing the tightness of the labor market become less over time. </span> <span id="sentence-3" data-timestamp="25:25" class="neutral bold">We're seeing inflation come down, and we're seeing wage growth come down. So monetary policy is in a good place. I think we've got interest rates in a place that is moving us gradually to our goals. I definitely don't feel urgency to cut interest rates. I think monetary policy is doing exactly what we'd like to see. Over time, the data will inform our decisions. I think eventually, my expectation is, as inflation gets all the way to 2% on a sustained basis, as the economy is in good balance,</span> <span id="sentence-4" data-timestamp="25:54" class="dovish bold">interest rates will need to be lower at some point, but the timing of that's driven by the economy. The economic data, like I said, are strong on the labor market, GDP, spending, and on inflation. It's a little bit of a bumpy road, but overall, the trend is that inflation is gradually coming down.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> Is there a possibility that the US economy is so hot that the Fed would consider actually raising rates? Because we've seen the recent retail spending numbers were stronger than expected. You talked about the jobs market. The last jobs number was kind of a blowout compared to what the expectations were. And we're seeing inflation not tick down in the way that the Fed had hoped for. Consumers seem to be feeling better, actually, where consumer sentiment had been the lagging factor, but now that seems to be getting better as well. So is there a possibility the Fed could even raise rates?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-5" data-timestamp="26:24" class="neutral">Well, it's not my baseline. My expectation right now is that interest rates are in a good place. Eventually, at some point,</span> <span id="sentence-6" data-timestamp="26:57" class="hawkish bold">we would want to lower interest rates as the economy really gets to the 2% inflation that we're headed towards. Of course, you never know what can happen. If the data are telling us that we would need higher interest rates to achieve our goals, then we would obviously want to do that. So it's not my base case. But one of the things we've learned over the past few years is it's hard to predict the future, and we need to adjust our policy stance as appropriate to achieve our goals.</span> <span id="sentence-7" data-timestamp="27:23" class="neutral bold"> I think one thing that's really important is when you hear 3% growth, 3 million jobs, or 275,000 jobs a month that we've been seeing in the first part of this year, it's in the context of a supply side of the economy that is really strong. We're seeing really strong labor force growth. We're seeing really good productivity growth. So these 3% numbers, I think, are driven in large part by strong supply and strong demand. </span> <span id="sentence-8" data-timestamp="27:52" class="neutral">That's why we can see these strong numbers, and at the same time, the unemployment rate is relatively flat at 3.8%, and we're seeing the imbalance in the labor market actually recede, not get tighter. So this is really more of a supply-driven expansion right now. And for monetary policy, we just need to make sure that demand and supply are in balance.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> Talking about not being able to predict the future, you talked about getting to that 2% target. For years, the Fed had undershot that target, and now it's overshooting it. We saw former Fed Chair Ben Bernanke do a major review of the Bank of England and its inflation modeling tools and forecasting tools, and basically, they've called for a major overhaul. Bernanke sort of detailed some of the failings. We obviously heard Fed Chair Powell walk back the whole "transitory" language, and maybe there was a better way to describe it in the past. Do you think that the Fed also needs a similar sort of postmortem review?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-9" data-timestamp="29:02" class="neutral">Well, first of all, I thought former Chairman Bernanke's report for the Bank of England was very good, and it made a lot of really important points. I think some of those points we at the Fed very much take to heart already. We need to constantly make sure we have the best economists, best analysts, the newest models, the newest data. The data we use at the Fed today is dramatically different than the data of the past. Obviously, we look at GDP and unemployment, </span> <span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="29:30" class="neutral">but now we have all this granular, high-frequency data from various different suppliers that's telling us what's happening in much finer detail, much quicker. So it's not nearly as backward-looking, and we were able to do that. That's something that we've embraced. I also think an important point that Ben Bernanke made was the importance of clear communication and transparency in monetary policy. This is something that in my career, the Fed has moved from being</span> <span id="sentence-11" data-timestamp="29:59" class="neutral">somewhat opaque to more and more transparent and clear, not only in setting our 2% inflation goal, explaining how we think about the economy, giving our projections and the dot plots, and all that to help, as best as we can, for the public to see how we're thinking, what's driving our decisions, and hopefully align the public's expectations with what we're trying to do. I think those have been hugely beneficial to us. These are things that former Chairman Bernanke mentioned in his report, things</span> <span id="sentence-12" data-timestamp="30:28" class="neutral">that I think we've been doing that have been very helpful. Down the road, obviously, as we get through this episode of the high inflation from the pandemic, Russia's war on Ukraine, and everything that's happened, we are looking carefully at our models, our analysis, the kind of conclusions we draw from that. And I think that assessment will be best done once this episode is kind of over, which I'm talking about in the</span> <span id="sentence-13" data-timestamp="30:58" class="neutral">next year or two, because then I think we'll get the full picture. If you had asked me two years ago what were the lessons of the pandemic and the war and everything, I think the answers we would have gotten would be incomplete and somewhat misleading. Now we've seen inflation come down pretty quickly around the world: in Europe, in Canada, in South America. Everywhere, we're seeing a very different dynamic. Let's see how that plays out, and then we will very carefully continue to</span> <span id="sentence-14" data-timestamp="31:24" class="neutral">study what are the lessons to how we can get better.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> Are there any sort of sacred cows, if you will, at the Fed? You mentioned the dot plot, which was in itself sort of an innovation after the crisis. Larry Summers mentioned yesterday that maybe the Fed shouldn't give so much forward guidance, that maybe messaging to the markets as often as you do after FOMC meetings, at hearings and that sort of thing, maybe that's too much communication. Are there some things that should be communicated more conservatively?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-15" data-timestamp="31:58" class="neutral">Well, clearly communicating on something like monetary policy, which depends on billions of people around the world and the economy and everything that happens, is always going to be challenging, no matter what the situation is. My personal view, I'm speaking for myself here, is that transparency has helped us. Doing things like providing multi-year projections, the chair's press conferences after meetings, these are helping people understand, whether we</span> <span id="sentence-16" data-timestamp="32:29" class="neutral">make the right decision or not, they're understanding the reasoning, the inputs that went into that. And obviously, we have to then adjust as the data come in and revisit our decisions every meeting and move forward. So I personally think the transparency has been helpful. We've seen inflation expectations, for example, basically around our 2% long-run goal before the pandemic. We got hit by the biggest shocks that we've experienced in generations. Let's be clear about this: these are the biggest</span> <span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="32:59" class="neutral">shocks around the world that we've seen in generations. And we did see inflation go up a lot, far too high. We saw inflation expectations move up. But as we and other central banks around the world took very strong, decisive action, inflation came back down. It's not all the way there. We still have work to do. But inflation expectations came down very quickly. So I think that the clear communication about our goals, about what we're thinking, and how we're viewing the economy has actually helped make</span> <span id="sentence-18" data-timestamp="33:27" class="neutral">monetary policy more effective in this period. There were times where you could look back and say, "Would you make a decision differently, or would you have communicated a decision differently?" Absolutely. If you can go back in the past and change things, there's a lot of things I would probably change in my life. But I think from the point of view of being effective, the transparency has been a big positive.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> What about the 2% goal itself? Should that be revisited? Is that something that would require global central bankers, because it had been basically a global goal of major monetary policymakers?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-19" data-timestamp="33:55" class="hawkish">So I have a one-word answer to that, and that's no. I think the 2% inflation goal is the right one. A lot of people ask me over the years, "Well, where did that 2% come from? Did you pull it out of a hat?" No, that came out of years and years of experience with countries around the world, years of very careful analysis about the pros and cons of inflation. If you</span> <span id="sentence-20" data-timestamp="34:29" class="neutral">have inflation and push it too low, you run into issues of hitting the lower bound or deflation. That's not good. If it's too high, that causes bad effects on the economy. I think the 2% inflation target has served us very well. Other countries have similar goals, of course, slightly different goals depending on the jurisdiction, and that makes sense. But I think for us, the 2% goal is really important. We have to not only have that goal, but we have to importantly achieve that and reinforce that</span> <span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="34:58" class="hawkish">credibility. As someone who's an academic economist in my background, it's easy to write papers, analyze at conferences, and debate, "Do people really care if inflation is a little higher?" And then you go and look at what happened the last few years. There wasn't anyone here in the United States or pretty much in any other country I know of that thought 7% inflation was a good thing, or 6%, or 5%. It's clear that low inflation is the bedrock of</span> <span id="sentence-22" data-timestamp="35:27" class="hawkish bold">prosperity. Stable price stability is absolutely essential. Theoretically, you can think about these things. In the real world, I think we need to have a low, stable inflation rate.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> I wanted to ask you about what's a bit of the elephant in the room during a lot of the meetings here: the prospect of another Trump presidency and what that means for the Fed in terms of its independence, its resiliency as an institution. We had seen Trump, when he was in office, call Fed Chair Jay Powell an enemy of the people, pressuring him to lower interest rates. Do you think that the Fed is up for possibly round two, and are you worried about the Fed as an institution?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-23" data-timestamp="36:02" class="neutral">I'm not worried about the Fed as an institution. Personally, I've been in the Fed now nearly 30 years. I've been on the FOMC 13 years. We are a group of people who get together, and we focus on one thing, and that's the economy, that's achieving our maximum employment and price stability goals. The world happens</span> <span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="36:35" class="neutral">around us. Of course, in Washington, D.C., there's politics, not just in election years, but any time. But we have a very clear mandate around monetary policy. We focus on that. You can read the transcripts. They come out five years later. Especially if you're having trouble sleeping, you can see that we spend eight hours [Fed joke, yeah, that's a Fed joke, it's like a dad joke] talking about the data in all of its details. And there's a wide range of</span> <span id="sentence-25" data-timestamp="37:02" class="neutral">views and disagreements. The wide range of views and disagreements are about how do we best achieve our goals. And there's a commitment to both our 2% inflation goal and our maximum employment goal. It's really just about getting that done. The best way to ensure independence of any central bank is to do our jobs well and focus on that.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> But are you worried about any challenges? They've been talking, possibly some of his advisors, about ways to lower the value of the dollar to make our exports cheaper, things that would just throw some obstacles in the Fed's way.</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-26" data-timestamp="37:31" class="neutral">Well, I'm not going to speculate on any hypothetical at all around any of those currency manipulation. I'm not going to engage in that. The value of the dollar, that's the domain of the administration, the US Treasury. Again, we're focused on monetary policy.</span></p>

<p><b>Gina Chan:</b> I know we're out of time. I just want to ask you really quickly, as you look forward, what are the things that you're keeping your eyes on that will help sort of influence your views on what the Fed should do going forward?</p>

<p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="38:02" class="neutral bold">I think one big question is this supply-side thing. We've seen this big increase in the labor force. We've seen very good productivity growth. Roll back the clock two years ago, there were a lot of concerns that the US economy wouldn't get back on track with the pandemic and everything. We are back on the growth track that we saw before the pandemic</span> <span id="sentence-28" data-timestamp="38:30" class="neutral">when you look at the overall economy. So watching if that continues, I mean, that's a very positive development for real incomes, for growth, and also for bringing inflation down. So that's one thing I'm very focused on. The second, clearly, is China, what happens in terms of their economy, their efforts to keep their growth near their target level, and especially given what's happened in real estate in China. So that's something to focus on. I think the third is the most</span> <span id="sentence-29" data-timestamp="38:57" class="neutral">important lesson again of my 13 years on the FOMC: expect the unexpected. <p><b>John Williams:</b> <span id="sentence-30" data-timestamp="38:57" class="neutral">well, last five or six years, we've learned the importance of planning and preparation and being nimble and agile in how you see what could happen, being prepared for things you didn't expect, not being locked into a certain view, but really coming into any situation thinking things can develop very differently and being able to adjust to that. So those are the things that I'm focused on.</span></p> <p><b>Gina Chan:</b> Great. Well, we'll have you back again to see how all of that plays out. Thank you so much, John.</p> <p><b>John Williams:</b> Thank you.</p>
</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Williams" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Powell Emphasizes Strong Labor Market and Persistent Inflation, Indicating Continued Restrictive Policy</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/16/powell.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Powell Emphasizes Strong Labor Market and Persistent Inflation, Indicating Continued Restrictive Policy" /><published>2024-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/16/powell</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/16/powell.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<h4 id="powell-excerpt">Powell Excerpt</h4>

<p><span class="neutral"><strong>Powell:</strong> Great.</span> <span class="neutral">So let me start by thanking Randy and Bill and Chavi and Tiff for this.</span> <span class="neutral">It's great to be here today.</span> <span class="neutral">I want to echo what Randy said about the mutually beneficial, respectful, great relationship we have with Canada, economically, culturally.</span> <span class="neutral">And I'd also like to echo I thought Tiff did a great job talking about the similarities and differences in our economy or financial markets, the challenges we face in our policy stance.</span> <span class="neutral">It's almost as though you have had a copy of that part of my remarks.</span> <span class="neutral">So I'm not going to repeat that but what I will do is talk if I could a little bit about the US economy and where we find ourselves right now.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">So as I think Randy pointed out, the performance of the US economy over the past year has really been quite strong.</span> <span class="neutral">We had growth of more than 3% last year as rebounding supplies supported both robust growth and in spending and also on employment alongside a considerable decline in inflation.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">More recent data shows solid growth and continued strength in the labor market, but also a lack of further progress so far this year on returning to our 2% inflation goal.</span> <span class="neutral">So I'll say a little bit about our two mandate goals, maximum employment and price stability.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish bold">As I mentioned, the labor market remains very strong payroll.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">Job gains have been strong over the first quarter averaging just a tick above 275,000 per month.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">The unemployment rate has been below 4% for 26 consecutive months, which hasn't happened in more than half a century, the longest streak of its kind.</span> <span class="neutral">Strong demand for workers has been met by a substantial increase in the workforce due both to rising labor force participation and a substantial increase in immigration as indeed Canada has experienced as well.</span> <span class="dovish bold">So even by with even with this strength, by many measures, our labor market has been moving into better balance over the past year.</span> <span class="dovish bold">The ratio of job openings to unemployed workers was extremely elevated in 2021 and 22, has now moved back down to levels just above the pre pandemic era.</span> <span class="dovish">Surveys of workers and businesses indicate a normalizing labor market.</span> <span class="dovish">So do the rates of both quits and hires and broader wage pressures also continue to moderate albeit gradually.</span> <span class="dovish">So the overall picture for the labor market is one of real strength, but gradual normalization.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Turning to price stability, or inflation mandate.</span> <span class="dovish">Inflation, of course declined quite significantly over the second half of last year, over the whole year, but particularly in the second half.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">But 12 month core PCE inflation which is one of the most important things we look at is estimated to have been little changed in march over February at 2.8%.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">In the three and six month, measures of inflation are actually above that level.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">So we've said at the FOMC that we'll need greater confidence that inflation is moving sustainably toward 2% Before the appropriate to ease policy.</span> <span class="hawkish">You know, we took that cautious approach and sought that greater confidence so as not to overreact to the string of low inflation readings that we had in the second half of last year.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">The recent data have clearly not given us greater confidence and instead indicates that it's likely to take longer than expected to achieve that confidence.</span> <span class="neutral bold">That said, we think policy is well positioned to handle the risks that we face.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">If higher inflation does persist, we can maintain the current level of restriction for as long as needed.</span> <span class="neutral bold">At the same time we have significant space to ease should the labor market unexpectedly weaken right now given the strength of the labor market and progress on inflation so far, it's appropriate to allow restrictive policy for their time to work and let the data and the evolving outlook guide us.</span> <span class="hawkish">We remain committed to returning inflation over time sustainably to 2%</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral"><strong>Powell:</strong> So to give you an idea, we do meet quite regularly.</span> <span class="neutral">So Tiff and I attend to G7 meetings per year for ministers, that's finance ministers and central bank governors.</span> <span class="neutral">We don't attend a leaders meeting but we attend i in the United States.</span> <span class="neutral">We attend the meetings with the finance ministers, which which Bill was and also to G20 meetings.</span> <span class="neutral">So that's two it's four meetings per year right there.</span> <span class="neutral">We also have six meetings at the Bank for International Settlements in Basel.</span> <span class="neutral">One of those is now virtual, but we're in and that's only central bankers, know, finance ministry.</span> <span class="neutral">So it's all central banking stuff.</span> <span class="neutral">And you know, it's economics, its financial regulation, all those things.</span> <span class="neutral">We also come here to Washington or every third year we go someplace else, twice a year for the IMF, World Bank meetings, which is kind of what everybody's doing in Washington right now.</span> <span class="neutral">So it's a lot of meetings.</span> <span class="neutral">What do we do with these meetings?</span> <span class="neutral">Fair question.</span> <span class="neutral">Essentially, we the central bankers are having an ongoing conversation about what's going on in their own economies and their own financial markets, their own regulatory world, with each other.</span> <span class="neutral">And we're also talking about the big global issues of the day, as you would expect.</span> <span class="neutral">So some of which are really the business of the elected government, not the business of central bankers, but we you know, we had that discussion.</span> <span class="neutral">It's more or less ongoing.</span> <span class="neutral">We're seeing each other all the time.</span> <span class="neutral">They're very informative, these discussions and they really are for me anyway, part of the way that I get to thinking about what the right policy is for the United States is to hear what is going on around the world what what what's happening globally, and how are people thinking about that?</span> <span class="neutral">So it's, it's very, very useful, particularly though given our close cultural financial, and economic ties with Canada.</span> <span class="neutral">Those discussions are especially fruitful, important and you know, I have regular conversations with Jeff by the way I do.</span> <span class="neutral">Keep very close track of the actions of the Bank of Canada I read TIfs press conference transcripts carefully, and pay close attention to that.</span> <span class="neutral">Tiff did mention the similarities and differences.</span> <span class="neutral">I will say one more thing, which is we we go to Basel as I mentioned five times a year, your long way from home and there usually is we're there for four or five nights and there usually one or two nights off, so we go looking for someone to have dinner with and very frequently we wind up with the Bank of Canada delegation for who are really good and very funny and a lot of fun together.</span> <span class="neutral">So we have a very close relationship with the bank and great respect for that institution, as I'll have a little more to say.</span> <span class="neutral">But lately, one of the things I'll point out though, about our relationship is we did do as Randy pointed out our first monetary policy first review of our monetary policy framework, really ever and we looked around and Canada also does regularly I think it's every four years.</span> <span class="neutral">In any case, we we really looked to the Canadian model and other models of how to do that.</span> <span class="neutral">We talked to people at the Bank of Canada about how their regular framework review went, so we really benefited for that.</span> </p>

<p><span class="neutral"><strong>Powell:</strong> So um, you know, our economies, our financial markets, solver institutions are deeply intertwined.</span> <span class="neutral">And when you when there is a situation where there's serious stress, you need to get a global perspective.</span> <span class="neutral">You need to get perspective around the world.</span> <span class="neutral">And you need you have to do that very quickly.</span> <span class="neutral">And we of course, can move effects quickly and effectively on the domestic front.</span> <span class="neutral">But what the thing that you you figure out in those times is that all the time you spent at Basel and at the g7 G 20 meetings, you know, your colleagues you know, and trust and respect their judgment.</span> <span class="neutral">And you don't have to go through that that phase of gaining trust in people you understand you understand each other, you speak the same language.</span> <span class="neutral">So there's a lot of communication, the level of communication is pretty high anyway, but during crises, it goes, it goes very high.</span> <span class="neutral">You're constantly talking to I'm constantly talking to other central bankers around the world and also political leaders in our government.</span> <span class="neutral">And that sort of thing.</span> <span class="neutral">So that happens a lot.</span> <span class="neutral">The sense of what you're doing, again, is mostly sharing information about what to do there may be a proposal that people are looking at and you're talking about that so it's, it's it's very useful.</span> <span class="neutral">I say.</span> <span class="neutral">One thing to point out is, it's less about coordination than it is about about talking and understanding it for one reason, or at least it was during the pandemic, and that was because almost every country's interest rates were very close to zero when the pandemic hit, and so there wasn't space.</span> <span class="neutral">There wasn't policy space for most economies, or central banks to do a big coordinated rate cut.</span> <span class="neutral">We did cut very quickly to zero, but we were I think we were higher than almost any other nation in terms of where our policy rate was.</span> <span class="neutral">But anyway, there's there's a lot of communication and those those relationships that you built up really do help at that point.</span> <span class="neutral">In terms of what we've, you asked about learning, what have we learned?</span> <span class="neutral">You know, I think that the pandemic is going to teach a whole lot of lessons over time.</span> <span class="neutral">I still think it's too early to say what they are with confidence and I'll point out look at the pandemic has surprised us over and over again, most recently by in the United States, the remarkably strong performance of the economy at a time when virtually all economists were expecting a recession.</span> <span class="neutral">So I think if you'd asked for the lessons of the pandemic a year and a half ago you'd get a very different answer.</span> <span class="neutral">Now, I think in I think in a year or so we'll have a lot more answers.</span> <span class="neutral">It's just it is a unique set of circumstances and we're still learning I think, but we will try to learn those lessons.</span> <span class="neutral">Different point I would say about the bank stresses another crisis, at least here in the States.</span> <span class="neutral">I do think we we can have learned the lessons of the stress of early last spring.</span> <span class="neutral">And I would point to a couple things that we embrace pretty forthrightly.</span> <span class="neutral">One was that supervision was not tightly focused on the right things was not proactive enough.</span> <span class="neutral">Was not forceful enough.</span> <span class="neutral">And we've taken steps to remedy that.</span> <span class="neutral">I also think there will be some regulatory initiatives for banks of that size and with those characteristics in time.</span> <span class="neutral">So I do think those those are lessons that that we that we have learned</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral"><strong>Powell:</strong> So I'll start by saying that each central bank serves a domestic mandate, which is in the case of Fed is using our tools to achieve maximum employment and price stability for the benefit of the people we serve.</span> <span class="neutral">So it's a domestic mandate, but in the case of the United States, we fully realize and appreciate that our decisions can take effects on not just on Canada but on Mexico but on countries around the world.</span> <span class="neutral">And that's all the more so because the dollar is the reserve principle reserve currency which strengthens the transmission of our policy through the global economy.</span> <span class="neutral">So we also know that those effects on global demand from our policy changes can have an effect on the United States as well that can rebound to the United States.</span> <span class="neutral">So we're very, very aware of all of that.</span> <span class="neutral">And for one thing we tried, we tried to be very transparent and predictable, given the flow, given the flow of data and events that you have to move quickly sometimes but we do realize we have a special obligation to be predictable and transparent.</span> <span class="neutral">And that benefits us in doing that as well.</span> <span class="neutral">So international spillovers of course are an important consideration.</span> <span class="neutral">We do track that.</span> <span class="neutral">Ultimately, though, we think over time, the most important thing we can do to support the global economy is to deliver on our mandate of price stability and maximum employment here in the United</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral"><strong>Powell:</strong> Specifically, specifically on inflation, I do think this is different.</span> <span class="neutral">This is not simply the more standard case of overheated demand, which has been the typical thing in the post war era for for the US economy and other major Western economies.</span> <span class="neutral">There are similarities and differences and I would characterize it that this way that the inflation that arose suddenly really in in the early part of 2021, as economies reopened resulted both from constrained supply and also elevated and re channeled demand from services to goods.</span> <span class="neutral">So if you remember and you will, I'm sure will unexpected widespread shortages and supply chain failures on a scale not seen in recent memory.</span> <span class="neutral">In the US.</span> <span class="neutral">Several million people had left the labor labor force creating a severe labor shortage that was more fully felt once the economy reopened, leading to a huge spike in wages and but also in the ratio of job openings to unemployed workers.</span> <span class="neutral">So very unusual situation.</span> <span class="neutral">Households had elevated levels of savings and demand was very, very strong as well.</span> <span class="hawkish">So we thought this was different as we thought, have thought since since we've understood the situation, that restoring price stability would require both the unwinding of the pandemic related distortions to both supply and demand, as well as the effects of tight monetary policy on demand, which would give the supply side time and space to recover.</span> <span class="dovish">And we think today that we're seeing those two things working together to bring that and about.</span> <span class="dovish">And you saw that I think in 2020, which was really in a large way a supply side story.</span> <span class="dovish">What happened was the supply side really recovered in 2023.</span> <span class="neutral">We thought that it would recover in 2021 and 2022.</span> <span class="neutral">I was beginning to lose hope.</span> <span class="dovish">And then in 2023, you saw the shortages and the issues with with with trade pipelines.</span> <span class="dovish">Not fully resolved, but largely the result you saw the labor US labor force shortage alleviated by both higher participation among people who had dropped out of the workforce but also from immigration.</span> <span class="dovish">So that was the year of the supply side recovery.</span> <span class="dovish">And you saw the core inflation rates dropped by two full percentage points in the face of very strong growth.</span> <span class="dovish">So that can only be explained by the enormous increase in potential output supply side increase over that year.</span> <span class="neutral">So that's how I would say it's different this time.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Powell" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Williams Says Fed Policy Is in a Good Place as Inflation Gradually Slows</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/15/williams.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Williams Says Fed Policy Is in a Good Place as Inflation Gradually Slows" /><published>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/15/williams</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/15/williams.html"><![CDATA[<p>Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.</p>

<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}

  
</style>

<div id="youtube-player-container"></div>

<!-- Load the IFrame Player API code asynchronously -->
<script src="https://www.youtube.com/iframe_api"></script>

<script>
  var player;
  function onYouTubeIframeAPIReady() {
    player = new YT.Player('youtube-player-container', {
      height: '315',
      width: '560',
      videoId: 'sSzcqhGYcVM'
    });
  };

function seekToTime(timestamp) {
  var timeArr = timestamp.split(":");
  var hours = 0;
  var minutes = 0;
  var seconds = 0;

  // Check if the timestamp includes hours
  if (timeArr.length === 3) {
    hours = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[2], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 2) {
    // If the timestamp is only minutes and seconds
    minutes = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[1], 10);
  } else if (timeArr.length === 1) {
    // If the timestamp is only seconds
    seconds = parseInt(timeArr[0], 10);
  }

  // Calculate total seconds
  var totalSeconds = hours * 3600 + minutes * 60 + seconds;

  // Seek to the specified time if possible
  if (player && player.seekTo) {
    player.seekTo(totalSeconds, true);
  }
}


// Attach click event listeners to each sentence
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function() {
  document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(span) {
    span.addEventListener("click", function() {
      // Remove highlighting/underscore from all spans
      document.querySelectorAll("span[data-timestamp]").forEach(function(otherSpan) {
        otherSpan.classList.remove("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      });
      
      // Add highlighting/underscore to the clicked span
      this.classList.add("underscored"); // or "underscored" for underscore
      
      // Seek the video to the timestamp
      var timestamp = this.getAttribute("data-timestamp");
      seekToTime(timestamp);
    });
  });
});

</script>

<h4 id="qa-transcript">Q&amp;A Transcript</h4>

<p><span id="sentence-1" data-timestamp="00:00" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> Numbers just came out pretty amazing.</span> <span id="sentence-2" data-timestamp="00:03" class="neutral">Are you continually surprised by the American consumer?</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-3" data-timestamp="00:06" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, first of all, welcome to the New York Fed.</span> <span id="sentence-4" data-timestamp="00:09" class="neutral">We're celebrating the 100th anniversary of this building here on Liberty Street.</span> <span id="sentence-5" data-timestamp="00:13" class="neutral bold">So consumer spending has been strong.</span> <span id="sentence-6" data-timestamp="00:15" class="neutral bold">I think it is driven by strong fundamentals.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-7" data-timestamp="00:18" class="hawkish bold">Job growth has been solid.</span> <span id="sentence-8" data-timestamp="00:20" class="hawkish bold">We've seen real wage gains.</span> <span id="sentence-9" data-timestamp="00:22" class="hawkish bold">We have we're in a pretty strong economy with good growth.</span> <span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="00:26" class="neutral">So, yes, it is part of that story.</span> <span id="sentence-11" data-timestamp="00:28" class="dovish bold">But, you know, I think what we're realizing is we're getting a nice tailwind from the supply side of the economy with good labor force growth, strong productivity, good real wage gains.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-12" data-timestamp="00:40" class="neutral">So with that, I think, you know, consumers are spending.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-13" data-timestamp="00:43" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> What's the thinking in your office and among your colleagues about does this last or is this a surprise that you think could go away at any minute?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-14" data-timestamp="00:53" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, one thing that makes it really hard to forecast is we're still feeling the effects of the after effects of the pandemic and Russia's war in Ukraine and all the things that have happened in between.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-15" data-timestamp="01:01" class="neutral">So we're definitely still seeing an adjustment process by the consumer, by in the economy overall.</span> <span id="sentence-16" data-timestamp="01:08" class="hawkish bold">But overall, I think that the economy will continue to grow at a solid rate this year, probably not as high as the 3.1% we saw last year, but something like 2% or around that.</span> <span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="01:18" class="hawkish">So I feel like we're still in a good place, probably not as rapid of growth as we saw last year.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-18" data-timestamp="01:22" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> Speaking of international events, I have to ask you, the Middle East going on right now.</span> <span id="sentence-19" data-timestamp="01:27" class="neutral">How do you think about the economic and policy implications of these events?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-20" data-timestamp="01:35" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Right.</span> <span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="01:35" class="neutral">So obviously, we're watching this very carefully.</span> <span id="sentence-22" data-timestamp="01:38" class="neutral">I think the primary way you see it to.</span> <span id="sentence-23" data-timestamp="01:40" class="neutral">How is, first of all, through commodity prices.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="01:43" class="dovish">But second is what we think of as a flight to safety, where investors, when they see risks in the global economy, they tend to bring money to the US dollar and that tends to push yields down somewhat.</span> <span id="sentence-25" data-timestamp="01:56" class="neutral bold">Right now, I think, you know, markets are pretty, pretty stable.</span> <span id="sentence-26" data-timestamp="01:59" class="neutral">We're not seeing big movements in that way.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="02:01" class="neutral">But generally that's the way I would... what I would expect to see when you see heightened geopolitical tensions.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-28" data-timestamp="02:09" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> When you think about what the markets are reacting to and what could come out of this, is this more of an inflation worry or a growth concern?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-29" data-timestamp="02:20" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, I it's really hard to say.</span> <span id="sentence-30" data-timestamp="02:22" class="neutral">It really depends on how the situation evolves.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-31" data-timestamp="02:24" class="neutral">Right now, I don't think of this as maybe in the near term, it could be effects of financial conditions in commodity prices, as I mentioned.</span> <span id="sentence-32" data-timestamp="02:34" class="neutral">I don't see this as a major driver of the overall forecast or outlook for economic growth or for inflation.</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-33" data-timestamp="02:40" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> Speaking of inflation, CPI came in much hotter than expected and sort of freaked everybody out on Wall Street.</span> <span id="sentence-34" data-timestamp="02:47" class="neutral">And markets sort of took that as a turning point in Fed policy.</span> <span id="sentence-35" data-timestamp="02:50" class="dovish bold">Do you see it that way?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-36" data-timestamp="02:51" class="dovish bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> I don't see it as a turning point.</span> <span id="sentence-37" data-timestamp="02:53" class="dovish bold">I think that, you know, we've we saw inflation come down maybe quicker than we expected last year.</span> <span id="sentence-38" data-timestamp="02:59" class="hawkish bold">We definitely saw really a lower readings in inflation in the final six months that I never thought that that was going to stay that low.</span> <span id="sentence-39" data-timestamp="03:05" class="neutral">That was kind of unusually low.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-40" data-timestamp="03:07" class="hawkish bold">We're now seeing some and a little bit unusually high readings.</span> <span id="sentence-41" data-timestamp="03:10" class="dovish bold">Overall, I think the picture is one that the economy is getting in better balance.</span> <span id="sentence-42" data-timestamp="03:17" class="hawkish bold">We still have a strong labor market and we're seeing inflation gradually come down.</span> <span id="sentence-43" data-timestamp="03:22" class="neutral">Now, I do think that, you know, for me, what do I see in the data?</span> <span id="sentence-44" data-timestamp="03:25" class="hawkish bold">Well, the economy and you pointed out the retail sales today, but more broadly, the economy continues to be strong.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-45" data-timestamp="03:32" class="hawkish bold">Again. I think we're being helped by strong demand and supply.</span> <span id="sentence-46" data-timestamp="03:35" class="hawkish">And those are helping, you know, growth.</span> <span id="sentence-47" data-timestamp="03:37" class="dovish bold">And we're seeing, you know, inflation come down a little bit slower than expected.</span> <span id="sentence-48" data-timestamp="03:42" class="neutral">And so, you know, I think markets are taking all of that information into account in how they how they expect policy to be.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-49" data-timestamp="03:48" class="neutral">For me, I'm, you know, data dependent, as always, really take the totality of the data and think about what it means for achieving our maximum employment and price stability goals.</span> <span id="sentence-50" data-timestamp="04:00" class="dovish">So I don't see this as a a game changer or anything.</span> <span id="sentence-51" data-timestamp="04:03" class="neutral">I do think it's important information that will clearly, you know, affect my thinking in my forecast.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-52" data-timestamp="04:11" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> Even those who have thought about what PCE might be after the PPI and CPI, inflation isn't coming down rapidly any more.</span> <span id="sentence-53" data-timestamp="04:15" class="hawkish bold">But you do have the strong growth.</span> <span id="sentence-54" data-timestamp="04:21" class="hawkish bold">You have very low unemployment.</span> <span id="sentence-55" data-timestamp="04:23" class="neutral">Why cut rates if the economy is doing fine at this level?</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-56" data-timestamp="04:20" class="hawkish bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, first of all, I think monetary policy is working at the rates we have now.</span> <span id="sentence-57" data-timestamp="04:28" class="hawkish bold">So I think I think monetary policy is in a good place over the past 12 to 18 months.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-58" data-timestamp="04:32" class="dovish bold">We've seen all pretty much all the measures of imbalances in the labor market enter our economy recede, many of them back to levels we saw in 2018 or 2019.</span> <span id="sentence-59" data-timestamp="04:40" class="dovish">So we're seeing that, you know, restoring balance in the economy.</span> <span id="sentence-60" data-timestamp="04:45" class="dovish bold">We are seeing a slow decline in inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-61" data-timestamp="04:50" class="hawkish bold">So I do think monetary policy right now is in a in a good place.</span> <span id="sentence-62" data-timestamp="04:53" class="neutral">I'm not fixated on where do rates need to go over the next year.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-63" data-timestamp="04:55" class="neutral">What I'm focused on is how do we best achieve our maximum employment and price stability goals?</span> <span id="sentence-64" data-timestamp="05:00" class="hawkish bold">The data we're seeing show the economy strong, and that's really good news and labor markets strong.</span> <span id="sentence-65" data-timestamp="05:06" class="dovish">At the same time, we are getting a better balance and we're seeing some declining overall inflation.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-66" data-timestamp="05:12" class="neutral">So for me, it's really about getting that right.</span> <span id="sentence-67" data-timestamp="05:14" class="neutral bold">And then whatever we need to do to adjust monetary policy, we can do to best continue the progress towards our goals.</span> <span id="sentence-68" data-timestamp="05:20" class="neutral">So that's how I'm thinking about it.</span> <span id="sentence-69" data-timestamp="05:23" class="neutral">And we just have to keep watching the data and make the decisions based on those goals.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-70" data-timestamp="05:28" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> What is your base case that you will cut rates this year?</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-71" data-timestamp="05:24" class="dovish bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> My own view is I think that with inflation continuing to gradually come down and I would guess I would say gradually is the operative word here.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-72" data-timestamp="05:34" class="hawkish bold">And with the economy remaining strong, I do think that given where the level of rates are, real interest rates now are considerably higher than they were before because inflation has come down quite a bit.</span> <span id="sentence-73" data-timestamp="05:47" class="dovish bold">So we will need to start a process at some point to bring interest rates back to more normal levels.</span> <span id="sentence-74" data-timestamp="05:55" class="dovish bold">And my own view is that we will you know, that process will likely start this year, but again, it will be driven, driven by the data and achieving our goals.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-75" data-timestamp="06:07" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> So it's possible you don't do anything this year.</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-76" data-timestamp="06:28" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, again, you're asking me to speculate on what will happen, of course.</span> <span id="sentence-77" data-timestamp="06:32" class="hawkish bold">And, you know, right now I think monetary policy is in a good place where we're seeing the but we're seeing progress.</span> <span id="sentence-78" data-timestamp="06:38" class="dovish bold">It's a bumpy road on the inflation front.</span> <span id="sentence-79" data-timestamp="06:41" class="neutral bold">And we'll just have to figure out how to best adjust policy as needed to achieve our goals.</span> 
  <p><span id="sentence-80" data-timestamp="06:45" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> You mentioned the real rate.</span><span id="sentence-81" data-timestamp="06:46" class="neutral">Is policy tight now?</span></p>
  
<p><span id="sentence-82" data-timestamp="06:48" class="hawkish bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> I do think we have restrictive monetary policy.</span> <span id="sentence-83" data-timestamp="06:51" class="hawkish bold">I do think policy is tight.</span> <span id="sentence-84" data-timestamp="06:53" class="neutral">So how do I what do I look for?</span> <span id="sentence-85" data-timestamp="06:55" class="hawkish">Because the economy's growing.</span> <span id="sentence-86" data-timestamp="06:57" class="hawkish bold">It grew over 3%.</span> <span id="sentence-87" data-timestamp="07:00" class="hawkish bold">You know, we're adding about, what, 275,000 jobs over the first three months.</span> <span id="sentence-88" data-timestamp="07:05" class="hawkish">So that seems like an economy that's really strong and not being held back by monetary policy.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-89" data-timestamp="07:13" class="dovish bold">But if you take a step back, all these measures of imbalances in the labor market, whether job openings or wage rates or quits rates or all the other indicators we look at, all of them are moving from being very tight to less tied, and most of them back to a more strong labor market or getting closer there.</span> <span id="sentence-90" data-timestamp="07:31" class="dovish bold">I mean, job openings are still high, wage growth is still a bit high, but these are all moving in the right direction.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-91" data-timestamp="07:39" class="dovish bold">So I think the stance on monetary policy is really been an important driver of restoring balance in the economy and helping bring inflation to 2% towards 2%.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-92" data-timestamp="07:49" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> What's left with inflation?</span> <span id="sentence-93" data-timestamp="07:51" class="neutral">Is it something that you can affect or are these non interest rate responsive sectors?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-94" data-timestamp="07:57" class="neutral bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> You know, monetary policy can affect inflation in the economy.</span> <span id="sentence-95" data-timestamp="08:00" class="neutral bold">It works through multiple channels.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-96" data-timestamp="08:02" class="neutral">So there are some sectors that maybe are not as interest sensitive, but the economy is interest rate sensitive.</span> <span id="sentence-97" data-timestamp="08:09" class="dovish bold">We've seen that over the past couple of years as we've moved from an accommodative policy to a restrictive policy.</span> <span id="sentence-98" data-timestamp="08:15" class="hawkish bold">So monetary policy is working as expected, to continue to work to to bring inflation down.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-99" data-timestamp="08:23" class="neutral">You're going to see it, you know, show up in different parts of the inflation, you know, goods versus services and things.</span> <span id="sentence-100" data-timestamp="08:30" class="dovish bold">But over the past year, year and a half, we have seen a broad based decline in inflation in all of these categories.</span> <span id="sentence-101" data-timestamp="08:39" class="dovish bold">It's just that we haven't gotten all the way to 2%.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-102" data-timestamp="08:42" class="neutral bold">And we just need to keep policy in the right place to achieve that 2% goal.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-103" data-timestamp="08:47" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> Question I always ask is what are CEOs companies telling you these days about their hiring plans, about what they're having to pay and about inflation, whether they're raising prices or having to pay higher prices?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-104" data-timestamp="09:02" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, clearly, if you asked me this question a year or two ago, that's all they would be talking about.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-105" data-timestamp="09:09" class="hawkish">Price increases, compensation increases, the challenges of hiring employees today.</span> <span id="sentence-106" data-timestamp="09:16" class="dovish">I think those you know, those comments are still out there a little bit, but far less than before.</span> <span id="sentence-107" data-timestamp="09:21" class="dovish bold">We're hearing from our contacts, you know, that it's easier to fill positions than it used to be.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-108" data-timestamp="09:27" class="dovish bold">Wage compensation pressures are less and price pressures are are less.</span> <span id="sentence-109" data-timestamp="09:33" class="dovish">I think that's consistent with what we're seeing overall in the data.</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-110" data-timestamp="09:36" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> You're the potential growth guy.</span> <span id="sentence-111" data-timestamp="09:38" class="neutral">Has potential growth moved up?</span> 
  
<p><span id="sentence-112" data-timestamp="09:40" class="hawkish"><strong>John Williams:</strong> You know, I am getting more optimistic about potential growth in the economy, I think for a couple reasons.</span> <span id="sentence-113" data-timestamp="09:47" class="neutral">One is, you know, through the pandemic and everything that happened after that, I, like most people, had concerns that the supply side of the economy had had suffered, you know, damage the labor force and in terms of labor force participation.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-114" data-timestamp="10:06" class="hawkish bold"> And, you know, as we've watched the data over the past few years, we've seen an increase in labor force participation, increase in labor force growth, and we've seen a rebound in productivity.</span> <span id="sentence-115" data-timestamp="10:19" class="hawkish">Now, I'm not saying that we're in some, you know, new high growth kind of world, but I do think a potential growth is probably closer to 2% or a little higher, which is well above a lot of estimates in the past few years.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-116" data-timestamp="10:37" class="hawkish">And that's a very positive sign for us real incomes and for the economy and obviously for helping get inflation down.</span></p>
<p><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> <span id="sentence-117" data-timestamp="10:44" class="neutral">A question for all of our friends around us on trading desks.</span> <span id="sentence-118" data-timestamp="10:48" class="neutral">You had a briefing on QT at the last meeting from the Fed staff and members, according to the minutes, generally agreed that it should start soon.</span><span id="sentence-119" data-timestamp="11:01" class="neutral">Does that mean may or does that mean June?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-120" data-timestamp="11:04" class="neutral"><strong>John Williams:</strong> Well, I think we said fairly soon.</span> <span id="sentence-121" data-timestamp="11:06" class="neutral bold">And the you know, I think that the reasoning for slowing the pace of reduction of our balance sheet makes a lot of sense.</span> <span id="sentence-122" data-timestamp="11:14" class="neutral bold">It's a prudent course of action.</span> <span id="sentence-123" data-timestamp="11:17" class="neutral bold">We are decreasing the balance sheet quite rapidly.</span> <span id="sentence-124" data-timestamp="11:20" class="neutral bold">And and by slowing that, we'll have more ability to monitor, assess and analyze as we get eventually to an ample reserves kind of world that we're aiming for.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-125" data-timestamp="11:34" class="neutral bold">Everything is going with the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-126" data-timestamp="11:36" class="neutral">Everything is going exactly as planned and things are going well when we decide to slow the pace of the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-127" data-timestamp="11:43" class="neutral">That's a decision for the committee.</span> <span id="sentence-128" data-timestamp="11:45" class="neutral">No decision was made at the last meeting, but obviously we'll get together relatively soon and discuss this further.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-129" data-timestamp="11:55" class="neutral bold">But to me, this is a sign of success of the plans we laid out almost two years ago to reduce the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-130" data-timestamp="12:02" class="neutral bold">We've had very little disruption in markets.</span> <span id="sentence-131" data-timestamp="12:04" class="neutral bold">It's worked exactly as planned, and we're just executing on that plan and that's going very smoothly.</span></p>
<p><span id="sentence-132" data-timestamp="12:11" class="neutral"><strong>Michael McKee:</strong> So it could come before rate moves.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-133" data-timestamp="12:13" class="neutral bold"><strong>John Williams:</strong> You know, these are really separate issues.</span> <span id="sentence-134" data-timestamp="12:16" class="neutral">I mean, our numbers are shrinking the balance sheet.</span> <span id="sentence-135" data-timestamp="12:19" class="neutral bold">We're focused on getting to ample reserves on monetary policy.</span> <span id="sentence-136" data-timestamp="12:23" class="neutral bold">We're very focused on achieving our maximum employment and price stability goals.</span> <span id="sentence-137" data-timestamp="12:28" class="neutral">Those are different objectives.</span> <span id="sentence-138" data-timestamp="12:30" class="neutral bold">Those instruments can obviously move in different times in different ways.</span></p>

</p></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="QT" /><category term="Williams" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Editors note: click on each paragraph to jump to the corresponding part of the video. Please forgive that the timestamp is a fuzzy match.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Chicago Fed President Goolsbee Suggests Rate Cuts Depend on Inflation Path, Particularly Housing</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/goolsbee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chicago Fed President Goolsbee Suggests Rate Cuts Depend on Inflation Path, Particularly Housing" /><published>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/goolsbee</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/goolsbee.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}
  
</style>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://video.foxbusiness.com/v/embed.js?id=6350791007112&amp;w=466&amp;h=263"></script>
<noscript>Watch the latest video at <a href="https://www.foxbusiness.com">foxbusiness.com</a></noscript>

<h4 id="transcript">Transcript</h4>
<p><span id="sentence-1" data-timestamp="00:00" class="neutral">Neil: Good rates overwintered as zero control though it can affect that.</span> <span id="sentence-2" data-timestamp="00:06" class="neutral">Obviously, they continue to back up a little less so today but the 10 year is still in and out about four and a half percent, which is the highest bad since going back to last fall.</span> <span id="sentence-3" data-timestamp="00:17" class="hawkish bold">That's still weighing on stocks right now the Dow down 361 points NASDAQ at a deep sell off.</span> <span id="sentence-4" data-timestamp="00:23" class="neutral">That's almost erasing the gains we had yesterday, and keeping all the averages either negative on the week or very negative on the week ever Austen Goolsbee.</span> <span id="sentence-5" data-timestamp="00:32" class="neutral">He's the Chicago Federal Reserve Bank president delighted to have him.</span> <span id="sentence-6" data-timestamp="00:36" class="neutral">Austin, good to see you.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-7" data-timestamp="00:38" class="neutral">Goolsbee: Great to see again, Neil.</span> <span id="sentence-8" data-timestamp="00:41" class="neutral">So tell me exactly what the Senate does at the next meeting.</span> <span id="sentence-9" data-timestamp="00:45" class="neutral">Well as a great relief to my colleagues and as I always start, I do not speak for anyone else on the committee.</span> <span id="sentence-10" data-timestamp="00:52" class="neutral">I speak for myself.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-11" data-timestamp="00:54" class="neutral">Neil: Okay, now you've seen all these things were in environment, right it is cross currents.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-12" data-timestamp="00:59" class="neutral">Goolsbee: I was going to say we're an environment with just like you said with with cross currents.</span> <span id="sentence-13" data-timestamp="01:04" class="dovish">For the second half of 2023. We make good progress getting inflation rate down from the from the unbearable peaks that it had reached.</span> <span id="sentence-14" data-timestamp="01:13" class="dovish">And we did that without a recession, which was virtually unheard of.</span> <span id="sentence-15" data-timestamp="01:18" class="hawkish bold">And now at the start of this year, we've gotten multiple inflation readings that are higher than where we wanted them to be.</span> <span id="sentence-16" data-timestamp="01:25" class="neutral">And I always say one month is no months, but two months.</span> <span id="sentence-17" data-timestamp="01:28" class="hawkish bold">You got yourself a real month and now we got two to three months of CPI inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-18" data-timestamp="01:33" class="neutral">We'll see what happens on PCE inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-19" data-timestamp="01:36" class="hawkish bold">But we must get inflation back down to target.</span> <span id="sentence-20" data-timestamp="01:39" class="neutral">The law says that we need to maximize employment to stabilize prices.</span> <span id="sentence-21" data-timestamp="01:44" class="neutral">That's the dual mandate and if we're not getting the job done, we have to get the job.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-22" data-timestamp="01:50" class="neutral">Neil: We're told that PCE that personal consumers part of is a favorite of you and your fellow fed and that generally might show not all the time more stable inflation environment if it does, are we back to the consensus that had built for at least two rate cuts?</span> <span id="sentence-23" data-timestamp="02:06" class="neutral">Some are looking at three rate cuts or is that also a jump ball?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-24" data-timestamp="02:12" class="neutral">Goolsbee: Well, I don't like tying our hands to say what we're going to do and future meetings.</span> <span id="sentence-25" data-timestamp="02:17" class="neutral bold">I don't even like doing that for the upcoming meeting when we're still going to get a bunch of data between now and then much less for these meeting.</span> <span id="sentence-26" data-timestamp="02:23" class="neutral">What are you going to do in June and September and and at the end of the year.</span> <span id="sentence-27" data-timestamp="02:28" class="dovish">Now that said it's clear if you take the long arc on inflation, that we were at real highs, and that it has come way down from those highs.</span> <span id="sentence-28" data-timestamp="02:36" class="neutral bold">And if we start getting readings from the PCE inflation, which is the better measure and that's why the Fed mostly looks at that and that's what the target is on.</span> <span id="sentence-29" data-timestamp="02:45" class="dovish bold">If we start getting better readings that show us that that arc of inflation coming down is true. That will make us feel a lot better about where we are in terms of monetary policy environment.</span> <span id="sentence-30" data-timestamp="02:58" class="hawkish bold">If the PCE inflation is re reinflating, then like I say our job is stabilized prices and we will stabilize the prices</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-31" data-timestamp="03:07" class="neutral">Neil: which means you will not be cutting.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-32" data-timestamp="03:10" class="neutral">Goolsbee: I'm not gonna I'm not gonna commit to what the policy could be.</span> <span id="sentence-33" data-timestamp="03:14" class="neutral">Let's just look at the numbers.</span> <span id="sentence-34" data-timestamp="03:16" class="neutral">You know, the parent of the data dog caucus is is the is the one I like to be part of and we just got to get the numbers.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-35" data-timestamp="03:23" class="neutral">Neil: Okay.</span> <span id="sentence-36" data-timestamp="03:24" class="neutral">I was hoping to get you on a weak moment.</span> <span id="sentence-37" data-timestamp="03:26" class="neutral">Let me get serious and so I'll spend about the soft landing argument Are you confident that that that can still happen?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-38" data-timestamp="03:38" class="dovish">Goolsbee: I kept using the phrase the golden path for 2023 that it was the mother of all the soft landings that you could get inflation down without a big recession.</span> <span id="sentence-39" data-timestamp="03:48" class="dovish">And in 2023, we did that.</span> <span id="sentence-40" data-timestamp="03:51" class="neutral">Now this question of the last mile is a little harder.</span> <span id="sentence-41" data-timestamp="03:55" class="hawkish">We're not going to have as much of the beneficial supply developments that we had in 2023 as we go into 2024 and we're still dealing with this question of how persistent is the inflation?</span> <span id="sentence-42" data-timestamp="04:07" class="hawkish bold">For me, the most important number to be watching on the inflation front here in the immediate term is what is happening with housing inflation, which if you go into the components of core inflation, this housing we thought by now would be coming down.</span> <span id="sentence-43" data-timestamp="04:22" class="dovish">If you look at market rents, they have come down the inflation rate there has come down, but that has not yet showed up as we thought it would in the broader measures of inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-44" data-timestamp="04:33" class="hawkish bold">And if it does. housing costs in general, it's under the real estate market, housing costs in general, but it's what it's kind of a specific measure of housing costs, which is based on what the rental prices are an owner occupied rent equivalent.</span> <span id="sentence-45" data-timestamp="04:50" class="hawkish bold">If that doesn't go down to something like what it was pre COVID will have a hard time getting the overall back to target.</span> <span id="sentence-46" data-timestamp="04:58" class="neutral">So I that's something everybody we're a long way from.</span> <span id="sentence-47" data-timestamp="05:01" class="neutral">We're a long way from there a long way.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-48" data-timestamp="05:05" class="neutral">Neil: So let me step back.</span> <span id="sentence-49" data-timestamp="05:07" class="neutral">And get your sense then.</span> <span id="sentence-50" data-timestamp="05:08" class="neutral">The conundrum the Fed could be in because obviously, you don't want to keep this going on with with rates where they are, God forbid higher because the flip side of that is the soft landing you hope to get doesn't materialize and that you could throw the whole country into a recession.</span> <span id="sentence-51" data-timestamp="05:23" class="neutral">If you erred on the side of hiking rather than cutting.</span> <span id="sentence-52" data-timestamp="05:26" class="neutral">How do you weigh that?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-53" data-timestamp="05:30" class="neutral">Goolsbee: What look, this is why every central banker in the United States and around the world goes to sleep each night with indigestion is you got to you got to balance those things off.</span> <span id="sentence-54" data-timestamp="05:41" class="neutral bold">The way to square the circle, I think is we're mostly gonna just follow the data and see what happens.</span> <span id="sentence-55" data-timestamp="05:47" class="neutral">The law gives us the dual mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-56" data-timestamp="05:49" class="dovish bold">And if we're getting inflation down, then the real rate the the rate that we set minus the inflation rate, which is kind of a level of restrictiveness.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-57" data-timestamp="06:03" class="dovish bold">Even if you're holding the rate steady as inflation falls, you're tightening the restrictiveness.</span> <span id="sentence-58" data-timestamp="06:10" class="dovish bold">So if we see that inflation is on this path back down to 2%. Then we got to think do we want to remain as restrictive as we are right now for for a long period.</span> <span id="sentence-59" data-timestamp="06:21" class="hawkish bold">If inflation doesn't come down, then the the that answer is that for us. I mean, we have to get inflation down.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-60" data-timestamp="06:30" class="neutral">Neil: You can't control oil prices.</span> <span id="sentence-61" data-timestamp="06:32" class="hawkish bold">And they're the web admin spiking largely on some of this recent instability in the Middle East. So that's a wildcard for you right?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-62" data-timestamp="06:41" class="hawkish">Goolsbee: That's definitely a wildcard on two counts.</span> <span id="sentence-63" data-timestamp="06:44" class="hawkish bold">One is the price of oil and the price of gasoline go into the cost of living so for headline inflation, that goes in there, but it's a wild card on the second dimension, which is when the price of oil goes up.</span> <span id="sentence-64" data-timestamp="06:58" class="hawkish bold">That's a key component to the production of a whole bunch of things, and from FedEx drivers to manufacturing to et cetera.</span> <span id="sentence-65" data-timestamp="07:05" class="hawkish">And so that's a negative supply shock and we've seen over the decades what happens when you get negative supply shocks hitting the economy is not good.</span> <span id="sentence-66" data-timestamp="07:15" class="hawkish">It leads to more stagflation airy environment, so we're going to have to definitely keep an eye on commodity prices.</span> <span id="sentence-67" data-timestamp="07:22" class="neutral">In the meantime, we are in a presidential election year I think because we have all these fancy graphics here, Austin and special music.</span> <span id="sentence-68" data-timestamp="07:30" class="neutral">And I'm just wondering if Donald Trump got back into the Oval Office, he's made it clear he's no fan of Jerome Powell.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-69" data-timestamp="07:37" class="neutral">Neil: So he replaced him.</span> <span id="sentence-70" data-timestamp="07:39" class="neutral">What do you think of that?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-71" data-timestamp="07:42" class="neutral">Goolsbee: Well, when I became a Fed man, I stopped talking about elections and politics and partisan battles of the old days.</span> <span id="sentence-72" data-timestamp="07:50" class="neutral">The feds job is to go off to conditions we got a dual mandate.</span> <span id="sentence-73" data-timestamp="07:55" class="neutral">There's nothing in there that says anything about politics about the stock market or any</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-74" data-timestamp="08:01" class="neutral">Neil: Are you saying that the Fed ignores saying the Fed ignores all of that though, because he needs to look put that pressure must be unbearable, because when you have many saying that, you know, Jerome Powell wants to make you know, this a little bit better for Joe Biden to be reelected.</span> <span id="sentence-75" data-timestamp="08:18" class="neutral">Not that he can orchestrate that at the Fed, but that is his personal preference.</span> <span id="sentence-76" data-timestamp="08:23" class="neutral">If he had his druthers, I don't even know if that's true, but that none of that enters into the equation with you guys.</span> <span id="sentence-77" data-timestamp="08:29" class="neutral">You don't.</span> <span id="sentence-78" data-timestamp="08:30" class="neutral">You don't sort of see what's going on around you.</span> <span id="sentence-79" data-timestamp="08:32" class="neutral">It's the big old elephant in the room.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-80" data-timestamp="08:35" class="neutral">Goolsbee: Like I said, I don't speak for I'm not gonna speak for Jay Powell you can go you should have an interview with with chair Powell.</span> <span id="sentence-81" data-timestamp="08:44" class="neutral">And you can ask him, I know that if you use specifically Austin goes we're not influenced by it.</span> <span id="sentence-82" data-timestamp="08:51" class="neutral">I don't have any pressure.</span> <span id="sentence-83" data-timestamp="08:53" class="neutral">Okay, and go just go look at the minutes or the transcripts of the FOMC meetings.</span> <span id="sentence-84" data-timestamp="08:58" class="neutral">We put those out publicly.</span> <span id="sentence-85" data-timestamp="09:00" class="neutral">Yeah.</span> <span id="sentence-86" data-timestamp="09:01" class="neutral">It's not about politics.</span> <span id="sentence-87" data-timestamp="09:03" class="neutral bold">It's about the dual mandate, what's in the employment and the job market and what's happening to prices.</span> <span id="sentence-88" data-timestamp="09:09" class="neutral">That's what's going to drive our behavior and because we got to tune out the arguments about elections, that's not appropriate in in the Fed context.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-90" data-timestamp="09:19" class="neutral">Neil: So you also tune out the markets you say and I've heard a lot of your colleagues say the same thing.</span> <span id="sentence-91" data-timestamp="09:24" class="neutral">You don't pay attention to it, but the markets were clearly expecting, you know, three rate cuts.</span> <span id="sentence-92" data-timestamp="09:30" class="neutral">Now they're down to two some are down to one I believe Bank of America is down to none.</span> <span id="sentence-93" data-timestamp="09:35" class="neutral">They don't think rate cuts this year.</span> <span id="sentence-94" data-timestamp="09:36" class="neutral">I don't you don't want to get into those predictions.</span> <span id="sentence-95" data-timestamp="09:39" class="neutral">But you know, what you say in that regard, is the type of stuff that that rattles them that's been rattling the market of late with this backup and inflation or the perception that it's not totally worked yet.</span> <span id="sentence-96" data-timestamp="09:53" class="neutral">So they're kind of losing hope.</span> <span id="sentence-97" data-timestamp="09:54" class="neutral">What do you tell them?</span> <span id="sentence-98" data-timestamp="09:56" class="neutral">Do you just ignore that?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-99" data-timestamp="09:59" class="neutral">Goolsbee: I don't want them to feel bad.</span> <span id="sentence-100" data-timestamp="10:01" class="neutral">But yeah, you mostly ignore them.</span> <span id="sentence-101" data-timestamp="10:03" class="neutral">The thing is, like I say the the law says what we're supposed to be watching, and it's employment and inflation.</span> <span id="sentence-102" data-timestamp="10:12" class="neutral">It doesn't say anything about the stock market.</span> <span id="sentence-103" data-timestamp="10:14" class="neutral">And when we put out a summary of economic projections, where we make contingent predictions of what will be the appropriate policy and each member of the FOMC is asked individually, we don't debate it, we don't deliver it.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-104" data-timestamp="10:31" class="neutral">Neil: What do you think the median of those at the at the last go round was for three cuts in this UI, right?</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-105" data-timestamp="10:39" class="neutral">If you remember in December when we put it out the median of the FOMC said three cuts and the market immediately said well that must mean seven cuts so that's right.</span> <span id="sentence-106" data-timestamp="10:48" class="neutral">Part of me just can't ignore that you're gonna find out what you ignore that in the markets right?</span> <span id="sentence-107" data-timestamp="10:53" class="neutral">So you just you don't if it's down a few 100 points, I get it today.</span> <span id="sentence-108" data-timestamp="10:57" class="neutral">What that says all noise to you.</span></p>

<p><span id="sentence-109" data-timestamp="11:00" class="neutral">Goolsbee: I think that it's mostly noise.</span> <span id="sentence-110" data-timestamp="11:02" class="neutral">The thing to remember is financial conditions do affect the economy.</span> <span id="sentence-111" data-timestamp="11:07" class="neutral">They are like monetary policy, but only with a long lag.</span> <span id="sentence-112" data-timestamp="11:11" class="neutral">So what happens this week or next week?</span> <span id="sentence-113" data-timestamp="11:13" class="neutral">That's a part is noise.</span> <span id="sentence-114" data-timestamp="11:16" class="neutral">You can move what you're looking for is the longer live signal.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="Goolsbee" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kansas City Fed President Schmid Urges Monetary Policy to Remain Restrictive Until Inflation Returns to Target</title><link href="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/schmid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kansas City Fed President Schmid Urges Monetary Policy to Remain Restrictive Until Inflation Returns to Target" /><published>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/schmid</id><content type="html" xml:base="/jekyll-theme-yat/fedspeak/2024/04/12/schmid.html"><![CDATA[<style>
    body {
        font-family: Arial, sans-serif;
    }
    .neutral {
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .dovish {
        background-color: lightblue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-dovish {
        background-color: blue; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .hawkish {
        background-color: lightpink; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: black; /* Ensuring text color is readable */
    }
    .most-hawkish {
        background-color: red; /* Changed from color to background-color */
        color: white; /* Changing text color to white for readability */
    }
    .bold {
        font-weight: bold;
    }
  .underscored {
  text-decoration: underline;
}
</style>

<h4 id="link">Link</h4>
<p><a href="https://www.kansascityfed.org/speeches/the-importance-of-prices-and-price-stability-remarks/">Link</a></p>

<h4 id="speech-text">Speech Text</h4>

<p><span class="neutral">Thank you for the opportunity to speak today at the 2024 Agricultural Commodity Futures Conference hosted by the Commodity Futures Trading Commission and the Center for Risk Management Education Research at Kansas State University. A special thank you to our hosts, Joe Parcell and Emily Garwood from Kansas State, and Chuck Marvine and Russ Behnam from the CFTC. Russ was kind enough to provide the keynote for the Kansas City Fed's National Ag Credit Conference last month. These types of cross-institution events are crucial for helping us understand key economic issues in the agricultural sector.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Agriculture plays an important role in the economy, especially in this part of the country. While locally important, the factors that influence the ag economy are often global. Commodity markets are subject to shifting weather patterns, swings in global growth, and geopolitical developments. Commodity prices adjust quickly to these influences and provide a real-time signal on the balance between supply and demand. Commodity futures markets help communicate supply and demand conditions to a wider audience and allow users and producers to hedge price risk. The CFTC plays an important role in promoting the integrity and resilience of these markets through effective regulation.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Just as in commodity markets, prices and inflation in the broader economy also reflect the balance between supply and demand. And, as we have witnessed in recent years, a persistent imbalance between the two can lead to prolonged episodes of elevated price inflation.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">In my remarks this afternoon, I will offer my thoughts on the evolution of imbalances in our economy and their implications for our progress towards low and stable inflation as well as for the appropriate path of monetary policy.</span></p>

<h4 id="inflation-and-wages">Inflation and Wages</h4>

<p><span class="neutral">Congress has provided the Federal Reserve with two monetary policy mandates: price stability and maximum employment. The Fed interprets price stability to be consistent with a 2 percent inflation objective as measured by the annual change in the personal consumption expenditures (PCE) price index. This measure aims to capture price movements across the vast array of goods and services purchased by consumers.</span></p>

<p><span class="dovish">During the post-pandemic economic recovery, inflation surged above 7 percent, a 40-year high, as robust demand ran up against supply bottlenecks and constraints on production.</span> <span class="hawkish">Although inflation has stepped down significantly since the Fed began raising interest rates in 2022, it remains above the 2 percent definition of price stability. Inflation has surprised to the upside since the beginning of the year and has run at roughly a 4 percent annual rate during the first quarter.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">This recent data underscores what I believe is the need for the Federal Reserve to be patient as we wait for clear and convincing evidence that inflation is on track to sustainably return to 2 percent.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Looking ahead, I will be watching three factors to monitor progress towards our inflation goal:</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">First, the tightness of the labor market and consequent upward pressure on labor-intensive service prices.</span></p>

<p><span class="dovish">Second, the potential for an increased supply of labor to relieve labor market tightness.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">And third, the risk that renewed supply chain challenges could provide an unwelcome boost to inflation.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">Elaborating further on the first factor: Elevated services price inflation is now the primary driver of overall inflation in the economy.[1] For example, higher prices for healthcare services contributed significantly to the rebound in inflation since the beginning of the year. The production of many services tends to be labor intensive. As a result, strong services prices are being supported by the tightness of the labor market and the ongoing imbalance between the economy's demand for workers and the available supply of labor.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish bold">And the demand for labor continues to be strong. This is evidenced by robust hiring and elevated wage growth. So far this year, firms added an average of 270,000 jobs per month to their payrolls, far above the historical norm. Postings for new positions also remain elevated, while initial claims for unemployment insurance have remained low for some time now.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">Indirectly, the ongoing tightness in the labor market has also pushed up the cost of housing, an important contributor to the current strength of overall inflation. New work arrangements and changing preferences increased the demand for living space during and after the pandemic, leading to a rapid increase in house prices and rents. After peaking near 9 percent in 2022, rent inflation moderated significantly last year. However, the contribution of rents to overall inflation remains well above its the pre-pandemic rate. Research by staff at the Kansas City Fed suggests that the ongoing tightness in the labor market could keep rent inflation elevated for some time.[2] Job gains and wage increases put upward pressure on rents and housing prices as income growth increases household demand for additional and higher-quality living spaces.</span></p>

<p><span class="dovish">A second factor I will be watching is the outlook for the supply of labor. Last year, the economy experienced a large increase in the workforce, especially among women aged 25-55. In addition, the economy experienced a post-pandemic rebound in immigration over the last year. This improvement in the economy's ability to supply labor helped to ease tightness in the labor market.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">Despite these improvements in the supply of labor, wage growth continues to signal an imbalance between labor demand and the number of available workers to meet that demand. While wage growth has moderated from its recent peak, it remains elevated compared to early periods and likely is continuing to put upward pressure on services prices.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Looking beyond wages, the Kansas City Fed's Labor Market Conditions Indicators (LMCI) provide another way to measure the ongoing tightness in the labor market. These indicators, which are published monthly on the Kansas City Fed's website, summarize many different labor market variables into measures of activity and momentum.[3]According to the most recent LMCI, activity in the labor market remains well above its longer-run average level, suggesting that the labor market remains tight relative to its historical norm.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">A third thing I will be keeping an eye on is a potential reacceleration in goods inflation. As robust demand for goods ran up against supply bottlenecks during the post-pandemic recovery, prices for many goods rose rapidly and contributed significantly to the overall increase in inflation. While prices for goods have been roughly flat over the past year, recent disruptions to global shipping imply some upside risk to goods prices going forward. Relatedly, energy prices are also up significantly since the beginning of the year, which poses an additional headwind to sustainably low and stable inflation.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish bold">Ultimately, achieving better balance in the labor market will likely be necessary for Federal Reserve policymakers to deliver on our price stability mandate and achieve 2 percent inflation. However, uncertainty remains as to the role that improvements in labor supply will play versus slower labor demand in rebalancing labor markets. While I welcome the significant growth witnessed in the economy's workforce last year, it remains unclear whether this rapid pace of supply improvement will continue going forward.</span></p>

<h4 id="the-outlook-for-monetary-policy">The Outlook for Monetary Policy</h4>

<p><span class="hawkish bold">With inflation still running above 2 percent and labor markets still tight, it is appropriate that monetary policy remain restrictive. Over the past two years, the FOMC has raised the federal funds rate by over 500 basis points and has started to unwind the large portfolio of security holdings it amassed on its balance sheet. All of this is an effort to help rebalance demand and supply in the economy and restore price stability.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">Even with these actions, the demand for goods and services has displayed remarkable resilience to higher interest rates. The economy continues to grow at a pace well above its longer-run trend. Much of this increase in overall growth has been driven by strong consumer spending. With increasing house prices and equity markets near all-time highs, the strength of household balance sheets appears to be encouraging households to spend rather than save despite the high interest rates. Accordingly, the household savings rate remains near historic lows.</span></p>

<p><span class="dovish">Similarly, in the agricultural sector, although farm incomes are expected to be down this year, they remain above their pre-pandemic levels. While higher interest expenses and reduced incomes may be weighing on some highly leveraged producers, the overall financial picture in agriculture remains strong. Most lenders report that the credit quality of their farm portfolio has been strong, loan delinquencies are still historically low, and profits of recent years continue to support strong balance sheets. In addition, despite the increase in interest rates over the past two years, farmland values remain firm alongside relatively strong global demand for agricultural products. The strength of global demand for agricultural products is a topic we will explore further in an event next month in Omaha, where we will look forward to connecting with a variety of businesses tied to agriculture to hear their thoughts on longer-term factors shaping commodity markets.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">This ongoing resilience in the economy creates some uncertainty about the path of the federal funds rate that will be needed to restore price stability. With inflation running above target, economic growth continuing to show momentum, and elevated prices across a range of asset markets, the current stance of monetary policy is appropriate.</span> <span class="hawkish bold">Therefore, rather than preemptively adjust the policy rate, I would prefer to be patient and wait for clear and convincing evidence that inflation is on track to hit our 2 percent target before adjusting the stance of policy.</span></p>

<h4 id="the-outlook-for-the-federal-reserves-balance-sheet">The Outlook for the Federal Reserve’s Balance Sheet</h4>

<p><span class="neutral">Now, I'd like to turn to another one of the Fed's policy tools: its balance sheet. While the level of the federal funds rate has held steady since July of last year, the Fed has continued to shrink the size of its balance sheet. As I see it, reducing the Fed's balance sheet is important for two reasons. First, balance sheet reduction helps reduce the overall degree of policy accommodation at time when policy should remain restrictive. And second, moving towards a smaller balance sheet is important to lessen the Fed's footprint in financial markets.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">For some context, the balance sheet grew significantly as the Fed responded forcefully to the COVID-19 pandemic. To help stabilize the economy, the Federal Reserve purchased large quantities of Treasuries and agency mortgage-backed securities. These purchases were carried out to reduce long-term interest rates and ensure financial markets continued to function amid lockdowns and historic uncertainty. Consequently, the Fed's balance sheet more than doubled from just under $4.5 trillion in 2019 to nearly $9 trillion in 2022. To fund these purchases, the Federal Reserve expanded the quantity of reserves in the banking system.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Since June of 2022, the FOMC has reduced its holdings by more than $1.5 trillion. However, the balance sheet remains large and continues to put downward pressure on long-term interest rates. With inflation running above target, a tight labor market, and historically high equity valuations, the economy and financial markets no longer require support from a large central bank balance sheet. Rather, given the state of the economy, my preference is for a much smaller balance sheet with a shorter average maturity.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish">The Fed's large balance sheet and footprint can also obscure price signals and distort financial markets. Our holdings put downward pressure on longer-term rates and flatten the yield curve. This stresses the traditional model of borrowing and lending central to the health of many community banks. In addition, the Federal Reserve continues to hold a large fraction of the total outstanding stock of agency mortgage-backed securities. These significant holdings could distort the allocation of credit and lead to future imbalances. As the Committee discussed in its Principles for Reducing the Size of the Balance sheet,[4] I believe our balance sheet should primarily be composed of Treasury securities to minimize the effect of the Fed's holdings on the price and allocation of credit in the economy.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral bold">The Fed's large balance sheet is also suppressing price signals in funding markets. Fluctuations in interbank lending rates provide timely signals to market participants about liquidity conditions in funding markets. For some time now, the federal funds rate has traded consistently 7 basis points below the interest rate on reserve balances and shown no sensitivity to fluctuations in reserves. This suggests that liquidity remains abundant. These price signals imply that our current pace of balance sheet reduction is not creating strains in funding markets.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">However, unlike our previous balance sheet normalization in 2019, the Federal Reserve has established the Standing Repo Facility, and banks have shown a greater willingness to use the discount window. If runoff began to unexpectedly stress funding markets and the spreads in the interbank market rose significantly, these liquidity tools would be available to prevent a significant increase in short-term market interest rates. As we learn about broader liquidity demand in the system through these price signals, I believe it will be important to tolerate some more normal volatility in interest rates.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral bold">Tolerating some interest rate volatility during runoff could improve the longer-term health of funding markets, which may allow the financial system to operate with fewer reserves. With a constantly evolving financial system, the appropriate amount of reserves needed to efficiently conduct monetary policy will not be defined by a fixed quantity but rather the ability of the financial system to redistribute that liquidity as needed.</span></p>

<p><span class="neutral">Consistent with the theme of my remarks today, price signals from markets will be necessary to help properly allocate this liquidity. Stopping balance sheet runoff too early poses a risk of further weakening the channels of liquidity redistribution. Along these lines, completely smothering rate volatility could make the interbank market less resilient and sow the seeds of future financial market instability.</span></p>

<h4 id="conducting-policy-under-uncertainty">Conducting Policy Under Uncertainty</h4>

<p><span class="neutral">With various unknowns surrounding the macroeconomic outlook, knowing the exact future course of monetary policy is always difficult. Jim Collins, the author, has been influential in my thinking as a leader throughout my career. In his book, Great By Choice, he says that, "None of us can predict with certainty the twists and turns our lives will take." In a rapidly evolving economic and financial landscape only four years after the outbreak of a global pandemic, this statement resonates with me.</span></p>

<p><span class="hawkish bold">As a policymaker though, I am certain that my colleagues and I on the FOMC will take necessary actions to restore price stability and achieve maximum employment. For now, I view the current stance of monetary policy as appropriate to achieve those objectives. Going forward, I'll be watching for further signs of progress in returning inflation sustainably back to our 2 percent target.</span></p>]]></content><author><name>Contact at emsun at stanford dot edu</name></author><category term="Fedspeak" /><category term="policy" /><category term="QT" /><category term="Schmid" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>